<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second pacquet of advices and animadversions sent to the men of Shaftsbury, occasioned by several seditious pamphlets spread abroad to pervert the people since the publication of the former pacquet.</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08999646</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08999646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1290:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second pacquet of advices and animadversions sent to the men of Shaftsbury, occasioned by several seditious pamphlets spread abroad to pervert the people since the publication of the former pacquet.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Jonathan Edwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Marchamont Nedham--Wing and L.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Pamphlets.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42173:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Second Pacquet OF ADVICES AND ANIMADVERSIONS Sent to the men of SHAFTSBURY.</p>
            <p>OCCASIONED By ſeveral Seditious PAMPHLETS Spread abroad to pervert the People, ſince the publication of the former Pacquet.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PLUTARCH.</bibl> Ineſt omni Populo malignum quid, &amp; que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulum in Imperantes.</q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and are to be ſold by JONATHAN ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WIN, at the <hi>Three Roſes</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42173:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42173:2"/>
            <head>A SECOND PACQUET OF ADVICES &amp; ANIMADVERSIONS Sent to the men of SHAFTSBURY.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>May 7. 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are here in a New world, <hi>a world of Quiet,</hi> as you ſay you are in the Country; and 'tis come about we know not how, unleſs it be that God, in kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to theſe Kingdoms, and this Citie, was pleaſed to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Majeſtie, and his Miniſters, and his Parliament, with Wiſdom extraordinary, to divert a Deſigne that had been long a brewing, by ſome perſons both in and out of Parliament; in the firſt place to embroyl the Parliament within it Self; and then, as the natural Conſequence of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42173:3"/>
that, the three Kingdoms alſo inevitably in <hi>another Civil War.</hi> I know every particular man of them will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſay to me, as <hi>Hazael</hi> did to the <hi>Prophet, Is thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant a dog, that he ſhould do ſuch things?</hi> that he ſhould deſigne, in doing what he did, to bring on a <hi>Civil War?</hi> But let the Philoſopher anſwer him with an old Axiom, <hi>Qui vult Media ad Finem, vult etiam &amp; ipſum Finem, He who willeth the Means tending to the End, willeth alſo the End it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any one of the <hi>Projectors</hi> did ſuch things, as have been obſerved, in all times, to induce a War, then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion that perſon meant the bringing on of a War, if he could not otherwiſe bring about his own Ends: and 'tis eaſie to believe alſo, that he drew in as many as he could to accompliſh thoſe Ends. If the ſame Opinions and Principles that brought on the <hi>First War,</hi> be now again abroach, have we not cauſe to believe they meant, or may mean a <hi>Second?</hi> If the ſame <hi>Faction</hi> be at work again that contrived the <hi>First War,</hi> and they as ſevere with the King as they were with his Father in diſputing his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; ſeminating Fears and Jealouſies among the People, and new trimming the <hi>old Bridle and Saddle of Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> to run down the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> circumciſe the Crown, ſet <hi>Christ in the Throne</hi> (as they ever moſt Hypocritically pretended, to the ſhame of Chriſtianity) thereby to ride <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> and out-rant the Kingdom: If theſe things were deſigned and tranſacted, the Party form'd and ready inſtructed by Pamphlets ſpread in Citie and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and their hearts full of hope before the Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in <hi>February</hi> laſt to have accompliſhed their work, ſhall we yet doubt of their Intent becauſe they did not effect it? There is reaſon enough to inform our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, That they gave us the <hi>Premiſes,</hi> though they could not the <hi>Concluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42173:3"/>
If it be objected, that abundance of the engaged men, and moſt of thoſe that ſeem'd to favour the <hi>Faction,</hi> were never known to be affected for <hi>Presbytery,</hi> nor meant they any ſuch thing: To this I anſwer, Tis no matter whether they did affect and mean it, or no; we know what they muſt have done at laſt: For, if they once be drawn in to vote and act along with a Party, whoſe buſineſs hath been by Prints and otherwiſe, to cry down the <hi>National Church-Government</hi> of Biſhops, they muſt of neceſſity, after they come to be throughly engaged, run along with them to overthrow it, and erect the other in its room; they two, viz. <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> and <hi>Presbytery,</hi> being in the Proteſtant Churches the onely Competitors for the <hi>National Form:</hi> and as long as our Nation is, and is ever like to be, for the having of ſome ſuch Form, if the prime <hi>Leaders</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors</hi> lead you by the noſe to the driving out the one Form, they are not ſuch ſhallow Politicians, as not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that you, as well as they, will, of courſe, be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to ſet up the other: And your <hi>Leaders</hi> alſo themſelves, though perhaps they care for no Form nor Church, yet if they will hold the ground they may hap to get by your help; towards their own greatneſs and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, will be under the ſame neceſſity of ſetting it up, though they really never liked it, nor intended it before: yea, 'tis not improbable they may hap to come unto ſuch a paſs as to think well of the old Form again, after they by ruining it have obtained their own ambitious ends, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it may ſerve them better than any other Form, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the maintaining of them.</p>
            <p>A moſt pregnant Inſtance of ſuch a probability we have in the late <hi>Game</hi> plaid by <hi>Cromwel;</hi> who was one of the firſt for <hi>pulling down Biſhops,</hi> and effected it; and though he ſet up no <hi>Form Eccleſiaſtick</hi> in their ſtead, as long as he could carry on his Greatneſs without it; yet after he had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42173:4"/>
gain'd his <hi>Protectorſhip,</hi> he began to think of ſuch a <hi>Form</hi> to pleaſe the Nation; which not being to be done by an <hi>abſolute Presbyterial</hi> One, it being under an equal ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence both amongſt <hi>Royalists</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> I have been told, he caſt about another way to accommodate the matter; and that having but one ſtep higher to make, he meant, that once done, to have taken up a Church-form as like the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> as might be, by <hi>mincing a Medley of Biſhop and Presbyter together;</hi> ſo that after all, we ſhould have had Biſhops again; onely they were to have had a new Name, <hi>Superintendents,</hi> as they are called in ſome other Reformed Churches: that is, in plain Engliſh, a Chair-man to a Committee of Presbyters; that is to ſay, a <hi>Biſhop in Shackles;</hi> and conſequently, a <hi>Monarch in Bonds,</hi> under the <hi>Argier-Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline.</p>
            <q>(Sic idem jungat Vulpes, &amp; mulgeat Hircos.)</q>
            <p>Which had he lived to effect, he would have gain'd as much by it, as he that deſignes <hi>the milking of He-goats, and going to plow with Foxes.</hi> For though his device might have ſerved to pleaſe the ambition of ſome of his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee</hi> of <hi>Clergie-Triers</hi> which then ſate in <hi>Whitehal,</hi> by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating them to the Dignity of <hi>new-faſhion'd Biſhops;</hi> yet it could never have agreed long with his own high Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, to have born ſuch <hi>a Clog upon Government:</hi> So that he and they, after a little experience, would eaſily have agreed to <hi>part Stakes;</hi> the one to reſume the old Name and Power of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> the other of <hi>King;</hi> and ſo to have left all the <hi>Factions</hi> in the <hi>lurch,</hi> (ſo ſaid my Author) as the likelieſt way to have pleaſed the People, and themſelves too. And it may very well ſerve to inſtruct our little world concerning the fair Iſſue of a foul Civil War; and teach them what may be expected from another, if ever we ſhould be ſo fond as to believe our <hi>new Patriots,</hi> or be ſo mad after Change hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42173:4"/>
In the mean while, 'tis very pleaſant to look back as far as <hi>February,</hi> to contemplate the wiſdom of the <hi>Projectors</hi> and their Party, and upon what fine ſubtil Suppoſitions they grounded their matchleſs Confidence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They ſuppoſed, and that most politickly, That a whole Nation had lost its memory of things past; the</hi> Parliament <hi>its Loyalty; the</hi> Court <hi>its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; the</hi> King <hi>all care of his Crown and his People's Interest; the</hi> Clergie <hi>their care of the Church; the</hi> Citie <hi>their Prudence; the</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>their Senſes; and that</hi> one little Rook <hi>had run away with all the wiſdom and honesty in the Land; and that downright Treacheries, petty Cunnings, and plain Knave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, may paſs in this Age, to entitle a man to the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of</hi> Politick Prudence, <hi>which ought to be reverenced as a glorious Beam of Divine wiſdom, which never ſhines but in generous and faithful Spirits, and is never to be found but in the Temples of true Honour and Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They ſuppoſed moreover very cunningly; That Monarchies which uſed of old to last about</hi> Five hundred years, <hi>could not live now above</hi> Twenty: <hi>And that one and the ſame People might in one and the ſame Age, be cheated with the ſame</hi> Tricks: <hi>And that to bring this about, three Kingdoms, with three or four gay Speeches turned into</hi> Printed Paper-kites, <hi>might be led in a ſtring as the Boys are by theirs; and that no other Kite of the ſame Strain could be found to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter 'em.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They ſuppoſed likewiſe, That if a Lord or two would but turn Tenants in the City, and drive a Trade of Popularity upon the Old</hi> Exchange, <hi>their Lordſhips, being better metal than ordinary Citizens, might be leſs liable to</hi> Breaking: <hi>and that they could not chuſe but thrive, though every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy knew they were going to ſet up with no better Stock of Interest and Wit, than of thoſe that had</hi> broken before 'em.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:42173:5"/>
They yet more wittily ſuppoſed; <hi>That whereas our old World was (as they thought) to have been drown'd again, all their</hi> Creatures, <hi>though of different kinds, and enemies to each other, would most tamely and lovingly concur into the</hi> New Ark: <hi>Alſo that in the midst of this</hi> Flood, <hi>the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Kingdom might be ſet on fire, provided it were by</hi> Parliament-Wildfire; <hi>and that then they might ring the Bells backward</hi> with a Rope of Sand; <hi>and that when the Combustion ſhould be over, they might ſafely put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their pious Project of raiſing</hi> a new Fabrick, <hi>as good and lasting as the former</hi> Republican, <hi>with the most elegant mixture of all manner of</hi> Sects; <hi>every jot as agreeable for building</hi> Caſtles in the air, <hi>as lays of Ginger-bread and Marble, with untemper'd Morter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for a final Crowning of the whole work, they once more ſuppoſed; <hi>That for carrying on the World again after all this deſtruction, there might be a coupling of Beasts of</hi> Mortal Antipathies, <hi>to repleniſh the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much for Drolling with our <hi>Politick Drolls;</hi> for this kinde of Dreſs very well becomes 'em.</p>
            <p>Now in good earneſt for <hi>Animadverſion:</hi> And here I know not which end to begin at, the Subjects are ſo many: which is ſtrange; for, I thought this kinde of work would have been over; that the <hi>Faction</hi> would have been taken down by the late Correction. But behold incorrigible Malice againſt the whole Government, and new Attempts in Print, a ſwarm of Pamphlets, to revive their Deſigne, and ſeduce the People: Some printed a little before, and one ſo late as ſince the time of the Battel of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may remember, the buſineſs of the firſt PACQUET was to ſtrip the <hi>Faction</hi> out of all their <hi>Fine Pretences</hi> and <hi>Projects,</hi> which were delicately laid for Storming the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and the Lines of Circumvallation were drawn
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42173:5"/>
in Print, after the Model of their <hi>Master-Engineers</hi> in FORTY ONE; they began alſo to make their Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches after the ſame manner. They firſt fell upon the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal Quarter,</hi> and to that end they charged their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets here with all manner of Scandals againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and ſent them to their <hi>Friends in the Country.</hi> Next, they fell upon the <hi>Kings Court,</hi> His <hi>Favourites,</hi> and the <hi>chief Officers of State,</hi> not ſparing the <hi>King</hi> Himſelf; and then upon His High Court of Parliament, uſing all manner of Devices to embroil the two Houſes, and ſo entangle Affairs, that one Seſſion was fruſtrated after another; ſo that no Publike Buſineſs could be diſpatched, nor Supplies be had, to anſwer the moſt urgent Neceſſities of the King and Kingdom: by which means the preſent Parliament was made in a manner uſeleſs: and the Word was given out to the Multitude, to make an <hi>Out-cry</hi> for a <hi>new One.</hi> All which Contrivances are to bear Date from the time of <hi>one ſmall States-man</hi>'s being turn'd out of Service, as hath been already ſufficiently manifeſted. He and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotters cut out all this work before this laſt <hi>February-Seſſion;</hi> others that became troubleſome after the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then ſat down, were but his <hi>Journey-men.</hi> For then, ſeeing he had failed in all the former Inventions, to ſkrue on a <hi>New Parliament</hi> by breaking the neck of this, ſome Friends that had been pettifogging among <hi>Half-witted Lawyers,</hi> undertook to furniſh him with Weapons; that is to ſay, Arguments drawn out of <hi>Old Statutes,</hi> which have lain Dormant ſome Hundreds of years without execution or notice, to prove this Parliament null or Diſſolved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot bring it to their Bow; and that a <hi>luckie new one,</hi> ſo much long'd for by the <hi>Faction,</hi> ought to be called forthwith; they being confident to carry away the Bell at <hi>new Elections,</hi> to create a Houſe of Commons that ſhall do their Buſineſs one way, and the King's another, or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42173:6"/>
not at all. In purſuance whereof, they have ſent abroad other new Pamphlets, which I now ſhall make bold to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter as they come in my way, though 'tis reported one or two of them were written by one Lord, and that by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lord the reſt were promoted to the Penning, and then to the Preſs in a private corner.</p>
            <p>The firſt remarkable Pamphlet ſent abroad, with intent to break the Neck of this Parliament, is entituled, <hi>Some Conſiderations upon the Question, Whether the Parliament is diſſolved by its Prorogation</hi> for Fifteen Months: And the Title-page further ſaith, that the two Statutes upon which this Queſtion depends are,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>4 EDW. 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14.</bibl> Item, <hi>it is accorded, That a Parliament ſhall be holden every yeer once, and more often if need be.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>36 EDW. 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10.</bibl> Item, <hi>for maintenance of the ſaid Articles and Statutes, and redreſs of divers Miſchiefs and Grievances which dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happen, a Parliament ſhall be holden every yeer, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time was ordained by Statute.</hi>
            </q>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>From theſe <hi>Statutes</hi> the ſubſtance of what the <hi>Author</hi> argues is; <hi>That if the King be obliged by Law to hold a Parliament once every yeer, then he ought to call a new one every yeer. And if ſo, then he cannot Prorogue one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament above the Term of a yeer. But the last Prorogation</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42173:6"/>
                  <hi>of this preſent Parliament having been for Fifteen Months, which is Three Months beyond what the ancient Law and Custom allows for one Parliaments ſitting: Therefore that Prorogation being contrary to thoſe Statutes, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it Self must needs die, and can continue no longer to act as a Parliament, being by Law extinct and Diſſolved.</hi> This is the Sum of what the <hi>Faction</hi> alledges to deſtroy this Parliament.</p>
               <p>Lord! what a Thing is <hi>Pedantiſm</hi> in every Profeſſion! The ſhame and reproach of every Science and Sort of Learning; eſpecially of this of the <hi>Law;</hi> and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of that part of it which concerns the Conſtitution of the Crown and Kingdom, to the prejudice whereof no Conſtruction of Law whatſoever ought to be made, or will be made by any wiſe and weighty man. But there are a ſort of little Pedants, whoſe ſhallow Brains want <hi>Line and Plummet</hi> to ſound the depth of matters; whoſe Skulls are too narrow to comprehend the utmoſt Scope of Law: theſe are a ſort of Creatures that are wont to be carried away with mere Sounds of words; are too apt to be Captivated by <hi>Phanſie,</hi> and miſtake it to be Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as 'tis the manner of the <hi>profane Vulgar</hi> of this and every Profeſſion; and ſo not being fit to get Publike em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment from a King, are of little uſe but to torment the Law, by wreſting it for the ſervice of ſuch as are Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious and Seditious in his Kingdom. But now for an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to their Argument, take notice in the firſt place; That in all the Books lately printed by this ſort of men, to pervert the People's opinion againſt the legal continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Parliament, they are very careful to tickle them with frequent mentions of <hi>ancient Laws, the good old Laws and ancient Customs of England,</hi> and the like Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; which make a noiſe, and great Noiſes uſually take the weaker ſort of people; yea, and engage them too,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42173:7"/>
they believing of courſe that where moſt Clamour is, there muſt needs be moſt Right, eſpecially if it be thought that the wiſdom of our Fore-fathers, and their practice, be concerned in the Caſe. As for the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of <hi>Politick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions,</hi> I believe our Predeceſſors acted as far as they underſtood; and perhaps they underſtood what was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient in their time and ſtate of affairs to be done; but certainly they could not be ſo unwiſe as to do it <hi>eo animo,</hi> with an intent to tie up Poſterity to the ſame Rules as were then uſed, it being utterly impoſſible in matters which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to adminiſtration of Government; becauſe in the Torrent of Time there flow down innumerable Accidents both among our Selves and our Neighbour Nations, which induce unavoidable Alterations in every Age, and thoſe muſt of neceſſity introduce new Counſels and Rules and Forms of managing a Government, ſuitable to the Seaſon, that is to ſay, to the preſent poſture and condition of the People. For as in the preſervation of mens private bodies, ſo this Verſe following holds to be a Rule abſolute in ordering the <hi>Publike Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Sic quoniam variant Morbi variabimus Artes.</q>
               <p>As new diſorders in State ariſe and alter its former Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſo there muſt be variation in the method and means of Remedy, or elſe all runs to Ruine. And for this End <hi>Parliaments</hi> themſelves were firſt ordained, that Princes, in ſuch Caſes, might adviſe with them when they ſhall need their Advice, about the making of new Laws, or altering old Laws and Cuſtoms, as they ſhall ſee occaſion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we find by old Records, that our Forefathers, in conformity to this Reaſon, many times varied the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of Parliament, both as to its time of Meeting, its Number, its Manner of ſitting, and time of Continuance,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42173:7"/>
and other Circumſtances; yet we nowhere find them in any wiſe condemned for it, it being to be ſuppoſed they did what, in their times, was for the then publike Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience. For both before and after the <hi>Conquest</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were held <hi>Three times a year,</hi> viz. at <hi>Eaſter, Whitſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide,</hi> and <hi>Christmas,</hi> but for continuance no longer than the ſpace of <hi>Eight days</hi> for each time: but that Cuſtom continued not any conſiderable time after the Conqueſt, but received many Variations all along to the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, in whoſe days the fore-cited Statutes were made which give Occaſion to our preſent Diſputes.</p>
               <p>The Book call'd <hi>The Mirrour of Justice</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. that ſometimes thoſe Parliaments departed from that frequencie, and were held <hi>Twice a yeer:</hi> and in thoſe days there was no ſuch thing as a Houſe of Commons, as 'tis noted in Print, for that the Parliament conſiſted then <hi>onely of King and Lords;</hi> ſo that it were better for our Admirers of old Statutes and Cuſtoms, in ſome Caſes to bury ſome of them, rather than let their Brains run a madding up towards the <hi>Conquest</hi> and beyond, to revive them to give Rules for us to proceed by. Thus it was ſome time of old as to the <hi>quality</hi> of <hi>Parliament-members:</hi> and then as to their <hi>manner of Sitting,</hi> my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. <hi>Par.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. tells us, that in <hi>Edw.</hi> the Firſt's Reign, the Commons had no diſtinct Houſe to ſit in, and <hi>no Speaker,</hi> as it appears in the Treatiſe <hi>de Modo tenendi Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> And in 6 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. in divers places it appeareth, <hi>that the Lords and Commons ſat together,</hi> and had then <hi>no continual Speaker.</hi> And then as to the nature of the Power of the Commons Houſe, it would tend to little edification, to deſcribe and meaſure it by the Report of Ancient Records, Cuſtoms, and Proceedings; and the People would get nothing by it but this, even a diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſlenderneſs of thoſe Priviledges which they had
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42173:8"/>
of old, in compariſon of thoſe that by the Favour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of ſucceeding Kings they have enjoyed to this day.</p>
               <p>But <hi>thirdly,</hi> if Cuſtoms and Precedents of time paſt be of ſuch eſteem with this <hi>Author</hi> and the reſt of his Fellow-Scriblers, in their Printed Books, then let them tell me a reaſon why a Prince may not in his time make uſe of a Precedent made by a former Prince in a Buſineſs of the ſame nature, and for which that Prince was never found fault with after, till this Captious quarrelſome Age that we now live in. For this Author confeſſes, that Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> in the Fifth yeer of her Reign Prorogued the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament from the ſecond of <hi>October</hi> to the fifth of <hi>October</hi> of the yeer following, which was <hi>three days</hi> above a yeer, and in ſtrictneſs of Law, this Prorogation lately made <hi>Anno</hi> 1675. for Fifteen Months, which is <hi>three Months</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a year, is <hi>as good and valid in Law as that;</hi> (they are his very words) wherein he is ſo far in the right, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe three days or three months can, as to point of Law, make no difference in the Caſe, either of them being a lapſe of time beyond what this man and his Fellows do ſuppoſe as limited by thoſe Statutes for a Parliament's ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and conſequently for its Proroguing; becauſe if a Parliament cannot legally ſit longer than a yeer, it cannot be Prorogued to a longer time than the Law gives it a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But that a Parliament may ſit and act with full force and vigor longer than a yeer, there is no Law to be found that contradicts; and therefore 'tis to be ſuppoſed that an Argument drawn from thoſe two Statutes of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Argument <hi>ex Conſequenti,</hi> that is, an Argument grounded upon Conſequence, the Conſequence if good ought to be derived from a right interpretation of thoſe Statutes. Now the deciſion of the matter reſts onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, Which of the two Parties Judgements you will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42173:8"/>
rely upon as moſt likely to make right interpretation of the Statutes; whether upon our Author's Judgment and his Fellows, who appear to be parties concerned in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Factious deſigne and ſeaſon; or upon the Judgment of the Queen's Parliament, which ſat in a more Happie Seaſon, who doubtleſs could not be ignorant of thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes: but neither they, nor any Parliament or Perſon ſince that yeer of the Queen, ever found fault with her <hi>Prorogation</hi> as illegal; which, it's to be believed would have been done before this time, if that Parliament, or any ſucceeding Parliament, or Lawyer, or other perſon, before the time of the <hi>late Prorogation,</hi> had apprehended the Queen to be faulty in hers. Therefore 'tis to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that this Precedent of <hi>Prorogation</hi> made by that moſt excellent Princeſs is a good one; and that the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of thoſe Statutes made by this <hi>Author</hi> and his <hi>Fellows,</hi> to ſerve a <hi>Faction,</hi> towards the ruine of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is the wrong.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if the ſence of thoſe Statutes be taken as they would have it, <hi>viz.</hi> That no Parliament ought to ſit above a yeer, but a new one to be called within the yeer, why were not thoſe <hi>Statutes</hi> made uſe of before in Fifteen yeers time, to condemn the ſitting of this? It is ſtrange that no notable Lawyer ſhould in all that time affirm the illegality of it: But that onely ſome few <hi>Scarabees of the Law</hi> ſhould now, to bolſter up a <hi>Faction,</hi> be ſcribling their ſence upon the Statutes, when the ableſt have been, and are ſilent, is ridiculous.</p>
               <p>Beſides, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> conſider, that when his Majeſty now Regnant did in the 16 yeer of his Reign, Enact, That the <hi>Triennial Act</hi> paſſed by his Royal Father in his 16th yeer, ſhould be Repealed, for Reaſons in that Act of Repeal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: yet upon the humble Supplication of the Lords and Commons He did Declare, <hi>That hereafter the ſitting</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42173:9"/>
                  <hi>and holding of Parliaments ſhall not be intermitted or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continued above three yeers at the most: And that within three yeers after the determination of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo from time to time within three yeers after the determination of any other Parliament or Parliaments, or if there be occaſion, more often, your Majestie, your Heirs and Succeſſors, do iſſue out your Writs for calling, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and holding of another Parliament, to the end there may be a frequent calling, aſſembling, and holding of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments once in three yeers at the least.</hi> From which I collect theſe enſuing Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That by the word <hi>Three yeers after the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this preſent Parliament,</hi> it is implied by the Act, that the duration of this Parliament ſhall not be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended within any determinate time; and there was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, becauſe they had a tedious work to do, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Ruines of three Kingdoms waſted and unſetled by a long Civil War.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This appears farther by the ſubſequent words, which ſhew that the determinate Courſe of Parliaments ſet by the Act is meant onely for the future <hi>after the Diſſolution of this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Parliament had been ſitting four yeers when they form'd this Act: and therefore though they in the Act made mention of the two old Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third for holding a Parliament every yeer, yet it ſeems they did not then in their virgin-days conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be within the breach of thoſe Statutes for ſitting above a yeer, becauſe they were upon the making of this Act: which doubtleſs ſo many learned men as are in theſe honourable Houſes would never have preſumed to do, if their Sitting had by Law been limited to but a yeers time, for then they could not but have apprehended that the Laws they made in the three yeers before, muſt have been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42173:9"/>
null and void for want of legal power to make them, as well as all the Laws that they ſhould make afterward till this day. And what muſt the miſerable Conſequence of that have been? even to demoliſh all the <hi>new Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> which had been or were to be laid for the Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Eſtabliſhment of the Crown, Church, and State, in caſe the validity of their former Sitting and Acting had been queſtionable, as they would have been by ſuch bold Interpreters of Law, as I ſhall further make them appear to be, who preſume to advance their own Underſtandings above the Judgement of whole Bodies of Parliaments; which theſe men have done, and do, by Printed Books ſcattered like Wild-fire about the three Nations to ſet all in Combuſtion.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Fifthly,</hi> what if it ſhould appear a more conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Queſtion to be put, Whether thoſe two <hi>Old Statutes</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third be not of moſt force for the King? And truely there appears good reaſon to conclude in the <hi>Affirmative.</hi> The two Statutes may ſtand as <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative</hi> Memorials of the Judgement of Parliament in time paſt for the Peoples having a right to a frequencie of Parliaments, <hi>if need require,</hi> and no farther; but it is not to be believed, that ſo Victorious and Potent a King as <hi>Edward the Third,</hi> ever would have paſſed thoſe two Acts, if his Parliaments meaning had been to cut off that main Point of his <hi>Prerogative Royal,</hi> viz. the power of judging when 'tis fit or needful to call a Parliament, and when not: Nor is it at all likely that it was the Opinion of that Age, that the King had done ſo in paſſing thoſe Acts; but 'tis rather to be ſuppoſed, that that Parliament meant no more than this, That thoſe Statutes were inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be <hi>declarative of the Common Law,</hi> and of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's having Right by antient Cuſtom to Parliaments, and that as they had been, ſo they ſhould alſo be <hi>yeerly</hi> in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42173:10"/>
future, if judged neceſſary. For I would know of any man of an impartial Judgment, how it is poſſible to ſkrue out of thoſe Statutes any other Meaning, ſeeing the words <hi>[if need be]</hi> are words Hypothetical or Conditional, <hi>viz. ſuppoſing there be need,</hi> or <hi>upon Condition there be need.</hi> Hereby 'tis implied, that if in a yeers time there be no need, there is no obligation by Law from hence for the calling a Parliament always within the yeer. The Sum of all then is this; <hi>That if no need be, he need not call one.</hi> And who (I pray you) ought to be judge of this <hi>need,</hi> but the King, who is to Call? But what ſaith our Author of the <hi>Conſiderations</hi> to this? He hereupon turns <hi>Statute-Expoſitor</hi> and <hi>Objector,</hi> as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>CONSIDERATOR.</head>
                  <p>He ſaith this meaning of the Law is but a <hi>Phanſie; all our Properties, Rights, and Liberties, are bound up in thoſe LAWS of Annual Parliaments; and the King's Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with them cannot take place with any man that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the First of thoſe two Statutes;</hi> viz. That a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be holden every yeer once, OR more often if need be; <hi>by which words the King is left onely Judge of the need of a Parliament oftner than once a yeer.</hi> But <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King ſee need or no, he is abſolutely and perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily bound to hold a Parliament once a yeer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>This ſort of men are always up with a great Noiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Property, Right, and Liberty of the People,</hi> becauſe moſt men are wont to be taken with the mention of thoſe matters wherein their Good and well-being is concerned, and the <hi>Projecting Faction</hi> would be ſuppoſed to be the onely Advocates for them; but alas, this is the <hi>Faction</hi>'s
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42173:10"/>
old main Engine to <hi>catch Proſelytes</hi> among the injudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous part of the World, which are always much the <hi>major</hi> Part of Mankinde, who in the mean time are not able to judge whether Diſcourſes be made rationally or not, till the <hi>Sophiſms</hi> or Cheats of ſuch Crafty Writers be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. And verily I believe this Penman himſelf, if he had pleaſed, might have ſaved me the labour of diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for he writes more like a Lawyer than any of his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows: And therefore he could have told you, that the Law of <hi>England</hi> is as careful for the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the King, as it is for the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Subject; and whereas the Government of <hi>England</hi> hath in all Times, even from utmoſt Antiquity been for a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> the Laws have not left it deſtitute of Powers to preſerve it Self in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; and the People ought to be as zealous for the Conſervation of it by maintaining the Rights of the Crown, as they are for their own, becauſe thoſe alſo were Ordained for Publike good, and are as neceſſary as the other; and accordingly the eye of the Law hath been as tender of them as of the other, becauſe our Anceſtors in framing the Conſtitution of this Kingdom conceived the end of Government, which is Peace, publike Convenience, and Safety, could not well be attained without it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that in this the wiſdom of the Law was great of old, and ought greatly to be admired, is moſt evident, becauſe by late Experience we have found ſince 1641, that in <hi>pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Feathers</hi> of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> the People did put none in their own Caps but what made them look like <hi>Bedlams,</hi> and become really ſuch by running at laſt into <hi>Anarchy,</hi> mere Confuſion. It were endleſs to bring in here a citation of manifold Proviſions made by Law to preſerve the <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative;</hi> for, they are known to all men that have ſtudied the Law, and to moſt men that have not. And therefore in making Interpretations of Law about Government, we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42173:11"/>
are when we write, to carry an even hand betwixt what is Right for the King, and what is Right for the Subject; and not draw Concluſions on one ſide out of literal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and particular Sentences, but rather to derive them from the general Sence and Scope of all our Laws on both ſides compared one with another: and ſo ſhould this <hi>Conſiderator</hi> and his Fellows have done, if they had honeſt Intentions.</p>
               <p>Next, as to what he ſaith of the Peoples <hi>Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties being bound up in Annual Parliaments,</hi> 'tis ſo ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, that his Maſters of the <hi>Faction</hi> in 1641 would not underſtand it ſo: They before all things proclaimed to the World, that the onely way to preſerve the Rights and Liberties was, to have a Parliament of length ſufficient to ſit and diſpatch the Publike affairs; that is to ſay, they who pretended themſelves to be the great Patrons of the Peoples Rights, were ſo far from thinking thoſe Rights were bound up in yeerly Parliaments, that they would not be ſatisfied till they had an Act paſſed to impower them to ſit as many yeers as they pleaſed; which they never could with any face have demanded, if the opinion of Lawyers, or of the People of that time had been, that all our Rights had been ſo bound up in thoſe two Statutes, that to part with yeerly Parliaments had been to part with our Rights and Liberties. For it would then have ſavoured of too rank Hypocriſie before the Multitude, and have raiſed their Jealouſie againſt them, had they imagined, or ſhould any body have told them, that their Rights and Liberties were at Stake by ſuch proceeding of their <hi>Patrons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, conſider this preſent Parliament's proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thoſe days when but few men offer'd to finde fault with them: For when in the Sixteenth yeer of His now Majeſtie they paſſed that Act <hi>to prevent long intermiſſion</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:42173:11"/>
                  <hi>of Parliaments,</hi> it is plain that they were of another opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion than the <hi>Conſiderator</hi> and his Fellows: For, the words and ſcope of the Act ſhew they were exceeding tender of our Rights and Liberties; yet determined the time of Parliamentary Meetings to <hi>once in three yeers:</hi> which 'tis reaſon to believe they never would have done, if they had not underſtood our Rights and Liberties would have been better provided for by their <hi>Triennial</hi> than by yeerly Meetings. But now adays it is a ſmall matter with our Factious <hi>Leguleian Scriblers</hi> to form up Opinions upon forged Interpretations of Law, and prefer them before the Opinions of <hi>whole Parliamentary Bodies;</hi> whoſe Wiſdom ought to be reverenced as, and as it is, the Wiſdom of the whole Nation.</p>
               <p>In the next place conſider how ſlily the <hi>Conſiderator</hi> ſhuffles in his tranſcribing one of the two controverted Statutes: The firſt ſaith a Parliament ſhall be holden eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeer once, <hi>AND oftner if need be;</hi> but he writes <hi>OR oftner if need be,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>AND.</hi> It is not out of any inclination I have to <hi>Pedantick Niceties,</hi> or that I think it becomes any man to mingle Points of <hi>Philologie</hi> with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about matters of <hi>Politie,</hi> that I now begin to play the <hi>Grammaticaster:</hi> but when I perceive there is a crafty purpoſe in altering ſuch a ſmall Particle, when one is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in a ſentence in ſtead of the other, I ſuppoſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes me not to neglect it, eſpecially when it perverts the whole meaning of a Law. I dare appeal to the <hi>Ferula</hi> of Dr. <hi>Busby,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Grammarians,</hi> whether there be not a material difference in ſignification betwixt <hi>AND</hi> and <hi>OR,</hi> the former being a <hi>Copulative,</hi> the later a <hi>Disjunctive.</hi> Now the preſent Diſpute betwixt the <hi>Conſiderator</hi> and me being this, Whether the words <hi>[IF NEED BE]</hi> do refer onely to the <hi>later part of the Sentence,</hi> or to the <hi>whole Sentence,</hi> as he a few lines after expreſſeth, and would
<pb facs="tcp:42173:12"/>
have thoſe words to refer to the later part onely, and therefore would by foiſting in the <hi>Conjunction Disjunctive OR</hi> in ſtead of the <hi>Conjunction Copulative AND,</hi> diſ-joyn the ſaid words <hi>[IF NEED BE]</hi> from the firſt part of the Sentence, give me leave to ſay that he hereby would put upon us a moſt partial Artifice of Deluſion, and <hi>mere Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle:</hi> for by the word <hi>OR</hi> there may be ſome colour for his Conſtruction of the Law, that the King is Judge onely whether a Parliament ſhall be held <hi>oftner than once a yeer;</hi> whereas the <hi>Conjunction [AND]</hi> couples and joyns the ſence of the words <hi>[IF NEED BE]</hi> to the former part of the ſentence, and ſo the Statute ſpeaks plain for the King's being Sole Judge, whether there be need of calling Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments once a year, as well as whether there be need of calling them <hi>oftner</hi> than once a yeer: So that 'tis evident the Noble King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, and his Parliament, meant no ſuch matter as the <hi>Conſiderator</hi> and his <hi>Fellows,</hi> and as ſome other Profeſſors of the Law have hitherto miſunderſtood, contrary to the General ſence of Law in that part of our Laws which concerns the Eſtabliſhment of the Prerogative of our Kings, a very principal flower whereof is the Power of Calling and Diſſolving Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as often as they ſhall judge there is need: and the Practice of other Nations in all the World hath juſtified this, that it is the common Birth-right of <hi>Hereditary</hi> Kings to be ſole Judges of this Queſtion, Whether there be need, or no need, at all times, of Calling or of Diſmiſſing the Supreme Aſſemblies, unleſs they limit themſelves; but (you ſee) here is reaſon abſolute to conclude our King <hi>Edward</hi> did not intend to limit himſelf to <hi>yeerly Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> by the ſaid Statutes.</p>
               <p>And to make further proof of this, ſee again what is ſaid by the <hi>Conſiderator.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42173:12"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>CONSIDERATOR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the Kings of</hi> England <hi>have not duely nor conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved thoſe</hi> Statutes <hi>ever ſince their making, doth not render them of the leſs Force; becauſe 'tis an Offence in the King not to fulfil a Law.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Here he is pleaſed to acknowledge what cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have not obſerved thoſe <hi>Statutes</hi> ever ſince their making: which ſhews, that our ſucceeding Kings never thought themſelves obliged by them, or that King <hi>Edward</hi> intended it ſo, unleſs they ſhould ſee need, or at any time judge it neceſſary to call a Parliament. Beſides, we do not read of any Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Complaint about the omitting of <hi>YEERLY</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, till our <hi>Presbyterian Masters</hi> of the <hi>Faction</hi> in their <hi>Grand Remonſtrance</hi> 1641. charged it as a fault upon his Majeſties Father, under pretence of thoſe Statutes. And doubtleſs ſome of the foregoing Parliaments would have made complaint about Yeerly Omiſſion, had they believed Kings bound to Yeerly Parliaments: But that King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> and his Parliament which paſſed the Law, never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended or underſtood it in the <hi>Conſiderator</hi>'s ſence, is to be concluded from this moſt undeniably; That from the Fifth yeer of the ſaid King to the Eighth yeer, no Parliament was called; the reaſon was, becauſe he judged there was no need. Nor doth it appear that he did afterward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any ſuch certain <hi>Puncto</hi> of time in calling his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but doubtleſs 'tis in reaſon to be thought he would have been ſo tender of his own Law as to have obſerved it within the fifth or ſixth yeer, and not ſo ſoon have broken
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42173:13"/>
it, if he had thought himſelf obliged abſolutely to a yeer, becauſe it was but in the fourth year that he paſſed it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>CONSIDERATOR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Conſiderator) the King is the onely perſon that is meant or can be bound: For he it is that is to Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or Hold Parliaments, and therefore the Statutes intend to oblige Him, or elſe they intend nothing, and the Laws for Parliaments that ſecure our Religion, Properties, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, are become onely Advices and Counſels to the King, with no obligation further than the Kings preſent thoughts of their expedience.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>That the Obligation to a Yeerly Parliament lies no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the King than if in prudence he ſee <hi>there be need,</hi> is already proved from a Right Conſtruction of the words of the Statutes; and that this prudential power and part of the Kings Prerogative in Judging the expedience of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Parliaments <hi>at this or that time,</hi> as <hi>Affairs ſhall in His Judgement require,</hi> did remain undiminiſhed by the ſaid Statutes: And they intended onely this, which was enough, That ſeeing the People had an ancient Right by Cuſtom to have frequent Parliaments, the King accordingly ſhould oblige himſelf to call Parliaments ſo often as every yeer, or oftner if there ſhould be need: Whereupon it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that ſeeing in the interval of Parliament there nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought nor can be any Judge of the neceſſity but the King, theſe two Laws left the power of judging it in the <hi>Prerogative-Royal</hi> as they found it; and the then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gained this great Advantage for the People, that whereas they before had a <hi>Right by Custom and Common</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42173:13"/>
                  <hi>Law,</hi> they now obtain a right by <hi>Statute-Law</hi> too: which certainly ſo wiſe a King as <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. would never have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without <hi>a Salvo put in for his Prerogative,</hi> by the words <hi>IF NEED BE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover conſider, if thoſe <hi>Statutes</hi> ſhould be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe underſtood, <hi>viz.</hi> that the King <hi>ex debito</hi> were bound <hi>every yeer</hi> to call a Parliament, whether it would not have been a great Miſchief rather than Benefit to the People: For in thoſe days they that ſerved Members in Parliament were wont to take Wages for their Service; and that would have layn heavie upon every poor Burrough to have been bound to pay Wages due once a yeer, ſometimes oftner, to their <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> it being recoverable by Law againſt them; which peradventure would amount to more than their ſhare of payment of <hi>Subſidies.</hi> Again conſider, as this would empty their <hi>Purſes,</hi> ſo it would lade them with <hi>innumerable Laws,</hi> which are as grievous almoſt as to have none, as it hath been found in many Nations by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and therefore it is that <hi>Justinian</hi> hath been every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where praiſed for ſo excellent an Emperour, becauſe when all the Nations under the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire were even over-laid with multitudes of Laws, and groaned more under this <hi>Yoak</hi> than that of <hi>Taxes</hi> &amp; <hi>Tributes,</hi> he took care how to deliver the people from that vexatious Burthen, by cutting off the <hi>major</hi> unneceſſary part of the <hi>Imperial Statutes,</hi> and Digeſting the reſt into a tolerable Body. Therefore ſhould ſuch <hi>yeerly Parliaments</hi> be impoſed on us by Law, the Statutes would ſoon ſwell to the like into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable paſs, and tire the people out of fondneſs after ſo frequent Meetings as theſe Writers plead for, and would force Us to admit even againſt all Senſe and Reaſon. Therefore we have abundant cauſe to praiſe the Wiſdom of His Majeſtie and this His Parliament, that in the 16th yeer of his Reign they framed that moſt prudent <hi>Triennial</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:42173:14"/>
Law, which placeth a <hi>golden Mediocrity</hi> betwixt the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving too frequent Parliaments, and too long delay of them; and I muſt needs ſay His Majeſtie hath therein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, by limiting himſelf to call Parliaments hereafter, at <hi>Three yeers time</hi> after the determination of this, and after the determination of every ſucceeding Parliament, to be beyond all our Kings, and moſt gracious in condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Indulgence towards his people; that as the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> which ſet on work this <hi>Conſiderator</hi> and his <hi>Fellows</hi> to delude the Subjects, and beget in them an Opinion as if His Majeſtie intended to deprive them of their <hi>Old Laws</hi> and <hi>Rights to Parliaments,</hi> do appear now to be moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful towards Him: ſo I ſuppoſe their mouthes will henceforth be ſtopped, ſeeing they are ſecured by that new <hi>Triennial Act,</hi> in which they ought to bury all ſuch Diſputes for the future: which they muſt needs do, if they will caſt an eye upon the ſaid <hi>Act</hi> before they fall to diſputing, and perverting His Subjects.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Objection</hi> more give me leave to anſwer, becauſe it will be but in ſhort; 'tis this: That though the words <hi>[if need be]</hi> be in the firſt Statute, yet they are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the <hi>Second,</hi> which being paſſed Thirty two yeers after, muſt be underſtood therefore to be <hi>abſolute.</hi> But this I ſay, though the words be not there <hi>in terminis,</hi> yet other words are there which make thoſe to be neceſſarily underſtood; and they are theſe: <hi>[AS ANOTHER TIME WAS ORDAINED BY STAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TE.]</hi> The <hi>Statute</hi> meant here is the former of the two, which is of the Fourth of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third. The Iſſue then is this: That this later Statute, which is of the 36 of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, referring, (as by the word <hi>AS</hi> appears) to the former Statute, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more is Ordained here, but what was, and <hi>AS</hi> it was Ordained in the former; and ſo it can bear no other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation than what is proper to the former, and is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42173:14"/>
onely a <hi>Second Confirmation</hi> by Statute-Law of the Right by ancient Cuſtom which the People had before to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as often as they ſhould be needful; as it is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the firſt of the ſaid Statutes.</p>
               <p>So I have done with the <hi>Conſiderator:</hi> His <hi>Fellows,</hi> who do but ſteal out of him, ſhall be handled in the next place. One of them entitles his Book, <hi>THE LONG PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT DISSOLVED:</hi> But under that Title he means this Parliament, becauſe they have ſat Fourteen or Fifteen yeers, by reaſon of the world of work they have had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, to repair the large Breaches made within theſe Nations by a tedious <hi>Civil War:</hi> which they might have finiſhed before now, had not many impediments been caſt upon them by the Malice and Cunning of <hi>a restleſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Faction;</hi> whoſe glory it would be, above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things attainable in the World, if they could any way <hi>diſſolve this Parliament,</hi> or contrive how to make it End with diſgrace, <hi>re infectâ,</hi> that they may not have the honour of finiſhing that glorious <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of Church and State which they deſigne; but that themſelves <hi>(viz.</hi> the <hi>Faction)</hi> and the <hi>Forlorn Hope</hi> of their Party, might once more have the opportunity to play the <hi>Game</hi> they have prepared againſt the good time of trying their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune at <hi>New Elections.</hi> In the mean while, their Plot is laid every way to backbite this preſent <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and by odious Reflections upon the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> to make as many of the People as they can out of love with our <hi>ancient Monarchical Conſtitution of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> that they may introduce the <hi>New Model</hi> of their own. For this is certain, the <hi>Spiritual Drivers</hi> which they make uſe of, and muſt, will <hi>neither go nor drive</hi> (as the Proverb ſaith) unleſs the whole <hi>Civil Frame</hi> be form'd to a cleverly comportment with the <hi>Geneva-Patern;</hi> but will
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42173:15"/>
rather flie off and curſe them, in ſtead of <hi>Meroz,</hi> and all their Undertakings, as the <hi>Scotch General Aſſembly</hi> did Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> when by an Authority of Parliament there, he preſumed, without their Bleſſing, to enter <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Anno</hi> 1648. to have reſtored His Majeſtie's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>No <hi>Temporal Lordſhips</hi> muſt look to thrive by trink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with them, unleſs they will <hi>truckle</hi> to 'em too, and comply with their eternal Pride and Ambition in all <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natical</hi> as well as <hi>Claſſical</hi> Concernments; as thoſe <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie Lords</hi> and <hi>leading Commons</hi> who ſtaid in the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to act along with them, were fain to do in the yeers 1644, 1645, 1646. 'Tis worth the remembring how the <hi>Spiritual Aſſembly</hi> ſat and dictated Decrees to the <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> which the <hi>poor Senate</hi> always very tamely obeyed, and ſhaped into <hi>Ordinances</hi> as faſt as might be, to be hang'd about the necks of the People, who had e'n as good have been hang'd out of the way, as to have ſuffer'd the Intail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch a Slavery upon their Poſterity; the End whereof muſt have been, and, if we look not now about us, may, and muſt be again, to bring King and Parliament to the ſame <hi>truckling condition;</hi> which King <hi>James</hi> once moſt ſadly experienced in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in his wiſdom ſaw, after he came to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly return upon Him and His People here, if ever that <hi>Faction</hi> got afoot again, or a horſback; foraſmuch as 'tis the <hi>onely Faction</hi> that cannot be mended or put into a conſiſtence with <hi>Monarchy.</hi> By which you may ſee what is to be gotten by <hi>crying down Biſhops;</hi> which their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites of late have moſt ſtudiouſly done, both in <hi>Prints</hi> and by <hi>long Speeches:</hi> and what thoſe few Lords and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers muſt bring upon us at laſt, though perhaps they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it not, if ever to compaſs their own Ends they make uſe of that <hi>Malignant Faction:</hi> And know, that uſe them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42173:15"/>
they muſt, and be ruled by 'em too, if they weaken the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, legal Power, and Reverence due to <hi>Biſhops;</hi> the doing whereof will neceſſarily make way for the other, and give them the opportunities, for which they have, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove theſe hundred yeers, been <hi>ſowing of Tares,</hi> and <hi>plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> and <hi>watering</hi> them in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> Oh, that I had leiſure in this place to give a particular Account of them, what a <hi>Thorn</hi> they have been in the ſides of Princes and People in both the Kingdoms! The preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the like is to be expected onely from His Majeſty, and this <hi>preſent Parliament,</hi> who are ſure to Him and the Government by Law eſtabliſhed: And that is the reaſon why this <hi>Diſſolving Pamphleter,</hi> and his <hi>Fellows,</hi> are ſo hot for a Diſſolution of them, having <hi>ſet their Dice</hi> to make us undergo <hi>Hap-hazard</hi> by a <hi>New one;</hi> which muſt needs have leſs Ability, Experience, and Knowledge, than theſe that have been long practiſed, to promote and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage what is <hi>proper Parliamentary work</hi> in this difficult ſeaſon, to heal our Breaches, ſecure the Government, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and eaſe the People. But <hi>a new raw one</hi> (quoth the <hi>Faction) would be more fit for us to practiſe upon and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author of this Book may be called the <hi>Diſſolver,</hi> becauſe he would <hi>Diſſolve</hi> all immediatly: But having little of a Lawyer in him, he goes another way to work, and in ſtead of Reaſoning, he chiefly betakes himſelf to <hi>Oratory,</hi> to try what that will do among the People, with the help of fine Flaſhes of Wit. Therefore I ſhall make but ſhort work in diſpatching him, as he does to diſpatch this Parliament out of the way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:42173:16"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>DISSOLVER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Anceſtors had a glorious value and kindneſs for our Engliſh Liberties; therefore that they might have a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Aſſurance that their Liberties ſhould continue, it was Ordained,</hi> 36 EDW. 3. cap. 10. <hi>That for the maintenance of thoſe Liberties, and remedy of Miſchiefs and Grievances that daily happen, a Parliament ſhould be held once every yeer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>I cannot but note this <hi>Diſſolver</hi> to be a mere <hi>Shifter.</hi> He ſhifts that Statute of 4 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. out of the way, as a thing too hot for him to handle, becauſe of the words <hi>IF NEED BE.</hi> And as he lays that aſide; ſo next he turns <hi>Statute-clipper,</hi> cuts off the main Clauſe, which qualiſies the Sence of the <hi>Second Statute</hi> of the 36 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. The words of the Clauſe are, <hi>As at another time WAS OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAINED BY STAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TE:</hi> Now that other Statute here mentioned is the firſt Statute of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. which ordained, that Parliaments ſhall be holden once a yeer <hi>if need be,</hi> and more often <hi>if need be;</hi> that is to ſay, we ſhall have frequent Parliaments, and as frequent as heart can wiſh, <hi>IF NEED require.</hi> Juſt ſo much and no more was Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the former Statute. But who ſhall be Judge of this <hi>need,</hi> or who can be but the King, in whom the Law hath truſted the Calling of Parliaments? Therefore 'tis in Law to be ſuppoſed it may be inconvenient for Him to call a Parliament ſo often as every yeer, when in his Judgment He concludes it not needful ſo to do. So much for <hi>Clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Statute;</hi> a Crime as bad as Clipping the King's Coyn, if not worſe. But any thing muſt be done to ſerve the turn of <hi>Diſſolution.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:42173:16"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>DISSOLVER.</head>
                  <p>The reaſon (he ſaith) is becauſe <hi>this Parliament hath ſat ſo many years, till they are not the Repreſentatives of one half of the People of</hi> England: <hi>And the</hi> Gentry, <hi>who think themſelves born to have their ſhare in</hi> Ruling, <hi>as well as being</hi> Ruled, <hi>judge it a very hard thing upon them to be ſecluded from their hopes of having the honour to ſerve their King and Country in Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>A Share of <hi>Ruling</hi> as well as being <hi>Ruled!</hi> 'Tis very fine (ye men of <hi>Shaftsbury)</hi> this is ſo like the language of the <hi>Old Levellers,</hi> who were all for <hi>Ruling by Turns,</hi> that one might almoſt ſwear <hi>a ſmall Friend</hi> of yours was at the Penning it. He is always for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p and Ride,</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> and Rule alone, and ſo is the whole <hi>Faction;</hi> and that is the Reaſon why they are for a <hi>Tumbling-Cast</hi> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Rulers of Church and State. But what <hi>Gentry</hi> are thoſe who hanker after <hi>Rule?</hi> If to ſit and <hi>ſerve</hi> in Parliament be to <hi>Rule,</hi> this the Law never underſtood in <hi>England;</hi> and the <hi>Writ of Summons</hi> to Parliament ſaith no ſuch thing; the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Empire</hi> being veſted in the King and thoſe that are by Law deputed under Him for that purpoſe. It was never otherwiſe underſtood till that fatal Parliament in FORTY ONE, when they wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Rule</hi> out of the hand of the King and His inferiour Magiſtrates. There were then ſuch a Sort of <hi>Gentry</hi> got into the Houſe, though but few in compariſon of the whole number, that in order to the gaining of all <hi>Rule</hi> into their own hands, from their Fellow-Members as well as the King, firſt placed it in the hands of <hi>London-Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:42173:17"/>
till by <hi>Tumults</hi> and <hi>Tumultuous Voting</hi> they drave away the reſt of the <hi>Gentry</hi> as well as the King and the <hi>majority</hi> of the <hi>Lords,</hi> and never left till themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the onely <hi>Lords of Miſ-rule.</hi> Such <hi>Gentry</hi> as thoſe were, are they that now reckon of <hi>Ruling</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> one day or other, if they can but be rid of this, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the People to chuſe 'em, having to that end a great confidence in the ſtrength of the Tongues and Lungs of their <hi>Ambulatory Chaplains.</hi> The reſt of the Gentry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them well enough and all their Windings, and do very well know and are ſatisfied, that here is a full Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, all places of Members having been fill'd up by Election of new ones as faſt as they were vacant; and that a convenient duration of this Aſſembly of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Repreſentatives (as he calls them) is the <hi>only Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient</hi> to prevent the Deſigne of that reſtleſs <hi>Faction,</hi> in whoſe Service this <hi>Diſſolver</hi> and his <hi>Scribling Companions</hi> are liſted. And now to do the Feat, he ventures at mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Law too: and his Arguments are all ſumm'd up in what follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>DISSOLVER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the Statute of</hi> 4 EDW. 3. cap. 10. and 36 EDW. 3. cap. 14. <hi>and by other Statutes, a Parliament is to meet</hi> once within a yeer. <hi>But directly contrary to thoſe Statutes, this last</hi> Prorogation <hi>Order'd the Parliament not to meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a yeer, but ſome months after: and therefore either the</hi> Prorogation <hi>is null and void in Law, and conſequently the Sitting and Acting as a Parliament is at an end; or elſe by your Sitting and Acting you will admit and justifie, that a particular Order of the King is to be obey'd, though contrary to an Act of Parliament, and thereby ſubvert the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> England <hi>by Law. So alſo the King's Order is to</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:42173:17"/>
                     <hi>be obeyed against</hi> Magna Charta, Petition of Right, <hi>&amp;c. and we have neither life nor liberty ſecured unto us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then the <hi>Diſſolver,</hi> by vertue of the foregoing Lines, goes on to ſpend four or five pages in ſetting forth the great hazard of our <hi>Laws, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> as if all were true he ſaid, and concludes all are gone, <hi>if the Prorogation beyond twelve months were a good one;</hi> but he ſaith <hi>'tis null, and the Parliament null'd therewith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Such ſmall Faggots of Argumentation as theſe are now bound up in Books to fire the Nation if it be poſſible! They firſt make <hi>falſe</hi> Conſtructions of the two Statutes of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. telling the world the King is by them bound to <hi>hold a Parliament once within every yeer;</hi> and if we could grant that to be the Statutes meaning, then they might have ſome ſhadow of Reaſon to make Concluſions to their own mindes. But I have already made evident, that they either miſunderſtand the Statutes, or craftily wreſt the ſence of them: There is no intent in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, that Parliaments be call'd yeerly <hi>ex abſoluto,</hi> but they contain a clear <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> as a <hi>Salvo</hi> for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted legal Prerogative of the King, in the words <hi>IF NEED BE;</hi> ſo that 'tis ſuppoſed in the Statutes the King hath, by his Prerogative-Royal, <hi>a Right of Judging</hi> the time when it is needful to call a Parliament, becauſe He, and none but He can Call. Therefore 'tis to be admir'd there ſhould ſo many words be made about ſo plain a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs: For, were I never ſo much a <hi>Conſpirator</hi> in forming Devices for the Deſtruction of this Parliament, I would finde out ſome more ſolid <hi>Baſis</hi> to build my Arguments upon than <hi>a manifest Contradiction,</hi> or elſe certainly I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42173:18"/>
would for ſhame be ſilent: The <hi>two Statutes</hi> ſay, we ſhall have frequent Parliaments, and ſo frequent as once a yeer <hi>if there be need:</hi> But the <hi>Factious Diſſolver</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the ſence of them to be, that we ſhall have Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments once a yeer though there be <hi>no need;</hi> ſo that you ſee upon what a wretched Bottom he and the reſt of them do build their Argumentations, and the high-flown flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of diſcourſe which they ſo diligently Print and ſpread abroad, to deceive the weaker unwary People, and intoxicate them with diſaffection to this Parliament, and to the lawful Prerogative and Government of His Majeſty. But if they can make no better <hi>Squibs</hi> than this to <hi>blow up a Parliament,</hi> they had beſt give it over: for, the King not being bound up by Law within a yeer, he is at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Prorogue beyond the limit of a yeer, and ſo the <hi>Fifteen Months Prorogation</hi> was and is good, though it hath been ſeldom that there have been ſo long Proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: For, that is no Argument againſt the Wiſdom and Power of the King to exceed ſome days or months, if He ſeeth in prudence it be <hi>pro bono Publico,</hi> and that urgent Reaſons of State do require it: and there is nothing in all our Law that ſpeaks a ſyllable to the contrary, if right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider'd.</p>
               <p>Therefore to unwinde the Bottom which the <hi>Diſſolver</hi> hath entangled, let me with aſſurance determine this Point, which is the Standard by which you may meaſure all that they have ſaid or can ſay. If thoſe two Statutes did not confine the Parliament's ſitting to Twelve months, then the Kings Proroguing His Parliament to Fifteen months was no violation of the ſaid Statutes: If no Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute be thereby violated, then the Prorogation was and is good. If ſo, then the Parliament is as firm in Being as ever any Prorogued Parliament was or can be, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Laws which they have made or ſhall make
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42173:18"/>
after the Prorogation are as perfect and obligatory upon us as any other Laws that ever were made in this Nation: And 'tis (no queſtion) a Crime little leſs than an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour at the Subverſion of Parliament, for any perſons by Speeches or Prints, in or out of the Houſes, to carry on a Deſigne of arguing a Diſſolution of this, thereby to perſwade the People againſt Obedience and Submiſſion to it. Nor can this Aſſertion of mine be conſtrued, as if I maintained any thing in derogation of that <hi>Freedom of ſpeech</hi> which ought to be had in Parliament, and which I count abſolutely neceſſary for the Debate and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of the Grand Affairs. But then that <hi>freedom</hi> of ſpeech ought to be qualified with ſo much Modeſty and Reverence, as not to run to ſuch licentious diſcourſe as the Laws make <hi>Criminal:</hi> for, next to downright <hi>Treaſonous</hi> diſcourſe, none can be worſe than that which tends to the Violent Diſſolution of a Parliament; that is to ſay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King's conſent, or againſt His will. What then do they deſerve who have been ſuch buſie Speech-makers both in and out of Parliament, to bring that End about againſt the King's conſent, and againſt the Laws? Or that ſhall preſume to do it hereafter; ſeeing the two Houſes have given their Judgment in the Caſe, contrary to the interpretation of all Factious Penmen and Talkers?</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Diſſolver</hi> goes further than this, and takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf the perſon of the People of <hi>England,</hi> and in their Name falls to downright threatning of both Houſes of Parliament, in the following words.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>DISSOLVER.</head>
                  <p>Pages 9 and 10. <hi>This we ſay not, Gentlemen, by way of acknowledgment, that you are in a Legal capacity now, to do us either good or hurt; for your day is done, and your</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42173:19"/>
                     <hi>power expired; but that you may not like a Snuff ſmell ill after you are out. For, the reaſon why we more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly direct our ſelves to you is, becauſe of the Character you have born, that therefore you ſhould not ſeem ſo much as to give Prerogative the upper hand of the Law. That ſo however you have lived, yet all may ſay and witneſs for you, that you died well, and made a worthy End. If not, we hope the whole Nation will ſtrictly obſerve every man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, that to ſit a little longer yet, would ſacrifice to this</hi> Prorogation <hi>the very best of Laws, and in them all the Laws and Liberties of</hi> England. <hi>The two Statutes of</hi> EDW. 3. <hi>were declared to be in force by your Selves, in the Sixteenth yeer of the King, in the new</hi> Triennial Act <hi>then paſſed; and we are ſure there hath been no new Parliament ſince to Repeal them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>What need this phrentick impertinent Clauſe here at laſt, ſeeing that no man affirms thoſe two Statutes to be Repealed? Let them ſtand for ever as Laws, to ſhew that as we had and have a Right to a frequencie of Parliaments, ſo alſo that the King hath a Right of <hi>Prerogative</hi> to judge whether there be need of having them ſo often as every yeer. And thus much is to be underſtood alſo by the tenour of the new <hi>Triennial Act,</hi> paſſed by this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>to prevent Inconveniences hapning by the long inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Parliaments;</hi> for they name the two Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, but make no mention of a Right to Parliaments <hi>once every yeer,</hi> the words of the Act referring to thoſe Statutes, being theſe onely <hi>[becauſe by them Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments are to be held very often]</hi> which is the very ſame that I grant and affirm to be the meaning of the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes: and their not affirming a jot more than I do, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42173:19"/>
that they underſtood them no otherwiſe than I do, in general terms for a Declarative Frequencie; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within a yeer or oftner, they ſay not a word: touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which it is to be preſumed they would not have been ſilent, if they had underſtood it to be the Right of the People to have had certain Parliaments yeerly, whenas the Statutes declare not <hi>abſolutely,</hi> but onely with condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>IF NEED BE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe all mouthes ſhould be ſtopped, and no room left for an Objection which ill-minded heads, or jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, may make, and is made uſe of by theſe our <hi>Factious Book-makers,</hi> viz. that our having of Parliaments is by this means left to the King's pleaſure, when he pleaſe to judge them needful; behold, there is no reaſon for ſuch objecting, becauſe the nature of His power to judge I maintain not to be abſolute, whether we ſhall have Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or not; but whether it be needful to have one, or more, ſo oft as <hi>within every yeer.</hi> Therefore the high Wiſdom of this preſent Parliament is to be magniſied in contriving <hi>that new Triennial Act</hi> in ſuch a manner, as prevents all the frivolous Objections that may be made by any other perſons. For in the later end of the Act, they pray in theſe words: <hi>[That it may be Declared and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, And be it Declared and Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, That hereafter the Sitting and Holding of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ſhall not be intermitted or diſcontinued above Three years at the most; but that within Three yeers after the determination of this preſent Parliament, and ſo from time to time within Three yeers after the determination of any other Parliament or Parliaments, OR IF THERE BE OCCASION MORE OFTEN, your Majestie, your Heirs and Succeſſors, do iſſue out your Writs for Calling, Aſſembling, and Holding of another Parliament; to the end there may be a frequent Calling, Aſſembling, and Holding of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:42173:20"/>
                  <hi>once in Three yeers at the least.]</hi> What can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired more than this Act hath provided for? We have by it ſecured a Parliament every Three years after this is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; which is more than ever you had before. And if you will not be contented with my Sence in expounding the Two Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, take here the ſence and judgment of the whole Parliament; They have Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided alſo for yeerly Parliaments or oftner, in theſe words, <hi>IF THERE BE OCCASION,</hi> as fully as <hi>Edward</hi> the Third did by the words <hi>IF NEED BE</hi> in thoſe ancient Statutes, the Prerogative of the King being left here entire, to judge whether there be <hi>OCCASION,</hi> as it was in the former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes to judge whether there be <hi>NEED</hi> of Parliaments every yeer or not: And ſo you ſee 'tis the ſence of this Parliament declared in their Firſt days of Sitting many yeers ago, that no more than this was meant by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of King <hi>Edward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold alſo how great the Wiſdom, Conceſſion, and Tenderneſs of His Majeſtie hath been towards us in this Particular, that to remove all Fears and Jealouſies which Seditious men plant and nouriſh in the mindes of weak people, about His poſſible Delaying of Parliaments long, He did ſo graciouſly concur with his Parliament in the ſaid <hi>Triennial Act</hi> to ſecure us in the <hi>Golden mean</hi> (as I once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore told you) betwixt the having <hi>too frequent</hi> or <hi>too few</hi> Parliaments in time to come! Moſt ungrateful then are they, and moſt malicious, and the Peoples greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who by their dark deſperate Contrivances, have ſo many yeers been caſting Rubs in the way of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to interrupt and impede the Noble Work of Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is moſt likely to be done by them, or by none; and had not the <hi>Faction</hi> hindred, it had been done long ago; ſo that we might ere now have ſeen Parliaments in motion upon this fair Wheel of a well-ordered Succeſſion.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42173:20"/>
Judge then I pray you how little cauſe this Clamorous unreaſonable <hi>Diſſolver</hi> hath to revile this moſt Loyal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> or impute to them a ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of our Rights and Liberties, which every days tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action ſhews, when they are ſitting, they do moſt ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly maintain: Whereas if he and his <hi>Fellow-Diſſolvers</hi> might have their Ends to put an end to their Sitting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have done their Work, it would by experience be ſoon found the onely way to run us out into Anarchy, and that they have been the onely Bank that kept out the great Floud of endleſs Conteſts and Confuſions which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably would follow a preſent Diſſolution. I could, without the help of a ſpirit of Prophecie, give an account of all beforehand, had I time or room to tell you the Story.</p>
               <p>But now 'tis time to behold the <hi>DISSOLVER</hi>'s Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. He tells the Houſe <hi>The whole Nation will ſtrictly obſerve every man among them, that, to ſit a little longer, doth ſacrifice to the late Prorogation made in</hi> 1675. But this is not all: He proceeds further in more plain terms, as followeth, page 10 and 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>DISSOLVER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Do not think to ſalve your Authority by your own Vote: for We</hi> (that is, the men of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> the Faction) <hi>must tell you, that no Parliament which is not antecedently ſo, can make it ſelf a Parliament by Vote. Do not think the People of</hi> England <hi>will do that indignity to their Laws; that diſhonour to the Finger of God, which by ſo ſtupendious and over-ruling Providence hath Diſſolved you; or that diſſervice to their own Interest, as ever to acknowledge you any more for their</hi> Repreſentative. And pag. 17. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unleſs you will ſtand upon Record as Oppreſſors of all</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:42173:21"/>
                     <hi>the People of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And a little after he ſaith thus: <hi>It is onely your ſingle fear that the People will not chuſe you again, that can make you do ſo and ſo, becauſe you doubt they will credit you no more: for oppoſing the Interest of the People is never the way to be choſen again.</hi> And page 18. <hi>Pray you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>remember the former long Parliament, how the People unroosted them, and took ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon them, their Lives, their Liberties, and the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of most of them.</hi> And pag. 19. he addes, <hi>Let not the vain perſwaſion delude you, that no Precedent can be found that one Engliſh Parliament hath hang'd up another,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>An unprecedented Crime calls for an unprecedented Puniſhment; and we faithfully promiſe we will uſe our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most endeavours, when a new Parliament ſhall be called, to chuſe ſuch as ſhall,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo forth.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Hold, hold, SIR! what d'ye mean? you'll crack the Strings by and by which ſhould hang Us. What ſhall we have next! A <hi>Switzerland-Reformation!</hi> Muſt the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> of this Parliament all <hi>to the Pot</hi> when theſe <hi>Reformers</hi> can get a <hi>New one?</hi> And for no other cauſe but ſitting longer than thoſe our <hi>New Masters that wou'd be</hi> would have 'em? See how furiouſly the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> would ride if they could get into the Saddle: but they do well to tell us ſo before they have got a foot in the Stirrup.</p>
               <p>Me thinks, ye men of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> I ſee in this Book a Print of the <hi>Noble hand</hi> that wrote it, and of his heart too, which plainly threatens that he would, if he could, <hi>furniſh us</hi> with a <hi>Precedent,</hi> to teach Poſterity that <hi>One Parliament may hang another.</hi> What then would a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment quickly do with ſuch a <hi>DISSOLVER</hi> as this,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42173:21"/>
if they knew where to finde him out? But the <hi>ſinger of God</hi> (which he talks of) may ere long point him out <hi>in a ſtupendious manner,</hi> before he can bring about his brave intended <hi>DISSOL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the reſt of his Book to the very end, he goes raving on at the like rate, telling Stories of time paſt about the hanging of two <hi>Lord Chief Justices,</hi> and a <hi>Lawyer that was one of the Kings learned Counſel;</hi> and of <hi>three Judges, and of forty Judges more,</hi> and of <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley,</hi> in the Reigns of King <hi>Alfred, Edward</hi> the Third, <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth. But to what end is all this reckon'd up, unleſs it be to fluſh the Phantſies of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, right or wrong, againſt the good time of <hi>DISSOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VING,</hi> which is as much long'd-for by the <hi>Faction,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> long for the day of their yet-expected <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At length he comes to conclude with an <hi>Exhortation</hi> to the People, of Diſobedience to the Acts of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; That in the mean time <hi>they refuſe to pay Taxes, or obey any other of their Acts, without first trying their validity by due proceſs of Law.</hi> And he exhorts alſo the <hi>Juries, that upon Tryals they ſhould not finde against their neighbours.</hi> So here is the <hi>Trumpet blown</hi> outright for Rebellion. But ſeeing he hath been ſo plentiful in Stories out of our Chronicles about Examples of <hi>Hanging,</hi> he ſhould have been alſo on the Peoples ſide ſo charitable, as to inform them, how we nowhere in our Chronicle can finde a Rebelling againſt payment of Taxes, but it always ended in Hanging the <hi>Jack Cades,</hi> the <hi>Wat Tylers,</hi> and Captain <hi>Mendals,</hi> with all the like Predeceſſors of this <hi>Leading Diſſolver.</hi> But <hi>not a word of the Pudding:</hi> He is ſo tender of the People, that he will not fright 'em, his Buſineſs being to <hi>draw in</hi> as many and as faſt as he can. <hi>Mutiny, mutiny, my dear Country-men,</hi> (ſaid a Rebel in a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42173:22"/>
Stage-play) <hi>or elſe I ſhall be hang'd,</hi> &amp;c. So there is an End of the <hi>DISSOLVER,</hi> and his <hi>Threatnings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Seditious Pamphlet that came abroad, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared with the Title of <hi>A Seaſonable Question and an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Anſwer,</hi> &amp;c. I have view'd this <hi>Author</hi> very well: but after a ſtrict impartial Search of him all over, I finde that as to matter of <hi>Law</hi> he writes little, yea nothing at all, but what hath been ſaid in other words by the two foregoing Writers: yet becauſe he hath interwoven ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſubtil inſinuations under pretence of <hi>Law,</hi> and many Scandalous Additions; I am conſtrained to take him alſo in pieces, and more effectually diſſolve him, than he can the Parliament, the deſigne of this Pamphleter being the ſame with his fellows.</p>
               <p>And I am the more willing to tire my ſelf out at this Work, that His Majeſties good Subjects may be throughly informed of all that the <hi>Faction</hi> is able to alledge againſt the <hi>Legal existence</hi> and <hi>duration</hi> of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and then the better judge of the unreaſonableneſs of theſe mens Suggeſtions, which they ſcatter all over the Land to impoiſon the mindes of men, and prepare them for the old pious work of <hi>Rebelling,</hi> after the mode of FORTY ONE. For, as it was in the days of <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſo all the Deſignes they are now upon, do well agree with the Text, <hi>There is nothing new under the ſun.</hi> You ſhall ſee the old Game of <hi>Covenanting, Sequestring, Slaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Plundering, Committees, increaſe of Taxes,</hi> with all the ſhapes of <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> in Governments, and miſeries Acted over again, if theſe men may prevail. They are likely to give us nothing New but a <hi>New Parliament,</hi> and that ſhall be a <hi>Swinger,</hi> as the DISSOLVER hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed us, and told us he hath taken care for the <hi>New Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions:</hi> ſo that the <hi>Houſe</hi> ſhall appear New in its <hi>Out-ſide;</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:42173:22"/>
but in its <hi>In-ſide</hi> as like the <hi>Old one</hi> as one Nut is like another.</p>
               <p>Here perhaps ſome captious man of malice may be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to miſtake me, as if I did declaim againſt <hi>New Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</hi> But that I may prevent thoſe that lie at Catch, let them know I plead not againſt them; but the having of any other Parliament brought on by Factious Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Outcries, in Print or otherwiſe, till <hi>this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> hath finiſh'd the Work now in their hands, for Setling the Nation with ſure Laws and Proviſions againſt Renting and Tearing of it by manifold Factions. But to proceed.</p>
               <p>This Book which I am now to Diſſect, is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mere <hi>Fiction.</hi> It ſuppoſeth a <hi>Letter</hi> from a perſon new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen to ſit a Member of this Parliament; one that, before he would make ſo great a Journey to <hi>London,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires a Friend of his, a <hi>Bencher</hi> of the <hi>Temple, becauſe there hath been a great noiſe in the Country, that by Law Parliaments are to be held once a yeer, and that whereas this Parliament was Prorogued to three months above the term of a year, the Prorogation being thereby illegal, the Parliament must needs be null and in Law Diſſolved. And therefore he would be loth to come up two hundred miles to put his neck in a Nooſe by ſitting here as a Member, unleſs his friend the</hi> Bencher <hi>would ſatisfie him of the truth of the matter, and adviſe him to come.</hi> This is the ſum of the <hi>Question:</hi> and the Fable is ſo laid, forſooth, that the pretended <hi>Bencher</hi> undertakes to give him his <hi>Reſolution</hi> upon the Point.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>BENCHER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is a</hi> Queſtion <hi>of the greatest moment, that ever was moved in</hi> England, <hi>viz. Whether this Parliament be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:42173:23"/>
                     <hi>Diſſolved by the last Prorogation for fifteen months. He that will anſwer it ought first to conſider, whether a</hi> Prorogation <hi>ordered and continued beyond a year, can be made to agree with our Laws, and the Statutes of the Realm; particularly thoſe two Statutes of</hi> Edward <hi>the third, which were re-inforced by that Act of the ſixteenth</hi> Caroli primi; <hi>which was repealed by the Act of the ſixteenth</hi> Caroli ſecundi, <hi>wherein this Parliament acknowledged thoſe Statutes of</hi> Edw. 3. <hi>to be ſtill the Laws and Statutes of the Realm; and they in this Act enacted no Clauſe that abates their force.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>It is indeed a Queſtion of the <hi>greatest,</hi> and withal of the <hi>ſlightest moment</hi> that ever was in <hi>England:</hi> ſlight in the <hi>nature</hi> of it, but <hi>greatest</hi> in the <hi>Conſequence;</hi> and I will ſhew you how. That in its nature 'tis but ſlight and idle, appears moſt abundantly by what I have already given you in the former part of theſe <hi>Animadverſions.</hi> To which give me leave to adde alſo, that it had never been brought under Queſtion, if <hi>one man in a corner</hi> had not failed in all other Tricks to bring about an <hi>untimely Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> of the Parliament. For, as ſoon as ever he was lifted out of the Court, the former <hi>PACQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ET</hi> ſhew'd how bravely he plaid his Game in Parliament, by imbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quing both Houſes in Diſputes about <hi>Priviledges,</hi> which raiſed ſo many Broils to hinder them from diſpatch of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, that all good endeavours were made vain, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament it ſelf became a while uſeleſs to the King, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to do any thing to relieve the preſſing Neceſſities of the Kingdom; that ſo by tiring out the patience and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of Prince and people, there might have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd a willingneſs on all ſides, to admit of an Argument for this Parliaments <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> and the calling of his <hi>Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted New one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:42173:23"/>
But the effect of theſe his Artificial Contrivances ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been prevented by the Wiſdom of His Majeſtie and His Two Houſes, then he had recourſe to this laſt Device of <hi>picking a Hole,</hi> if poſſible, in this point of the <hi>Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> which, with the aſſiſtance of a few Diſaffected Lawyers and others, was preſently done, by falſe Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Gloſſes upon old Statutes; and from hence ſprang the Original of this frivolous Queſtion about the legality of this Parliament's longer Sitting; which they with more Impudence than Conſcience determine in the <hi>Negative,</hi> as hath been manifeſted unto you; ſo that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall concur with them, muſt obſtinately offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to his own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and all the known Rules of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, if after due Conſideration he ſhall adhere to their Opinion.</p>
               <p>Moreover, though the Queſtion in it ſelf be but ſlight, yet as to the Conſequence I agree it may be of exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moment, as the Deviſers thereof intended it. For, they meant to delude the people into a miſunderſtanding of the Laws, a Jealouſie of their Liberties, and a diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Tumults, to the hazard of their Peace, their Lives and Fortunes, by new Commotions. Their Deſigne is, by raiſing the duſt about this Queſtion, to put it in your eyes, that you may not diſcern Right from Wrong. Their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is to get themſelves; by the help of a <hi>Popular <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>proar,</hi> into a Governing poſture; and to this end they <hi>compaſs Sea and Land to make Proſelytes,</hi> to carry on a general Crucifixion of the preſent Governours; Cares and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, that is, a <hi>Crown of Thorns,</hi> they prepare for the head of the <hi>King,</hi> Scandals for his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> a <hi>Level</hi> for the <hi>Nobility,</hi> a Pitfal for the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> a Yoke for the <hi>Gentry,</hi> and a <hi>Fools Coat</hi> for all the <hi>Commons</hi> that they can ſeduce into their <hi>Party;</hi> in which they have leiſure to repent, and once more pay Taxes to fellow-Subjects, who (as ye
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42173:24"/>
may remember) do know how to ride you, being ready <hi>Booted</hi> and <hi>Spurr'd,</hi> if you pleaſe once more to <hi>ſet them on horſeback;</hi> till you ſigh and confeſs what a Poet ſaid of old,</p>
               <q>—Nec enim Libert as gratior extat Quàm Domino ſervire bono.—</q>
               <p>As for the two Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, you know I have granted, that the <hi>Triennial Act</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond doth not at all infringe their force; and I have told you I wiſh they may for ever ſtand to preſerve the <hi>Right of the King</hi> in calling frequent Parliaments <hi>when he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them neceſſary,</hi> as well as to maintain the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> in having them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>BENCHER.</head>
                  <p>He talks next of a Statute made in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond's Reign, <hi>That Parliaments be held yeerly to redreſs delays in Suits, and to end ſuch Caſes as the Judges doubt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo, that in the Ninth of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, the Duke of <hi>Gloucester</hi> told the King, <hi>That one old Statute and laudable Custom is approved,</hi> that <hi>the King once a yeer do ſummon his high Court of Parliament, as you may read in</hi> Grafton.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Firſt, you have onely <hi>Grafton</hi>'s word that the Duke of <hi>Gloucester</hi> ſaid ſo. And ſuppoſe the Duke did ſay ſo, you have onely the <hi>Duke</hi>'s ſaying for it; and he doth not name the time of that <hi>old Statute</hi>'s making: for, no ſuch Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute was in being till the time of <hi>Richard</hi>'s Grandfather,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42173:24"/>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> the third; and then that ſhort ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of time from him could not make any ſuch Statute an <hi>old one.</hi> But I grant there had been an ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of <hi>yeerly Parliaments,</hi> till at length the people grew weary of it; which (no doubt) was the reaſon why the Houſe of Commons in <hi>Edward</hi> the third's time, agreed to paſs <hi>thoſe Statutes,</hi> not to have them ſo frequent unleſs the King ſhould ſee need. For, this ſence is clearly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the very words of the firſt of the two Statutes, as I have ſhewn before. Beſides, I once again aſſure you, No ſuch Statute is to be found that ſaith any thing about the matter, in the times elder than <hi>Edward;</hi> onely there had been a Cuſtom, which the people held as lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble till they ſaw reaſon to alter it in that King <hi>Edward</hi>'s days.</p>
               <p>As for yeerly Parliaments <hi>to redreſs delays in Suits of Law,</hi> and end difficult Caſes, there is no ſuch Statute which he mentions to be found; nor is it likely that the Commons ſhould be called to ſuch kinde of work of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining ſuch Suits, they having never had juriſdiction ſo to do. Nor could it have been a Parliament, after the manner of the Parliamentary Conſtitution then in being, if the <hi>Lords</hi> had aſſembled <hi>alone</hi> to end Suits. Therefore it is in no wiſe likely that there ever was any Intention to make ſuch a Statute about the Calling of Parliaments yeerly to end ſuch Law-ſuits. Nor are ſuch difficult Suits as paſs the skill of the Judges, or ſo many of them, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening conſtantly in a yeers time, as to need a Parliament to end them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>BENCHER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ancient</hi> Britains <hi>(as</hi> Dunwallo <hi>writes) held Annual Parliaments four hundred yeers before Christ; and the</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:42173:25"/>
Mirrour of Juſtice <hi>ſaith, King</hi> Alfred <hi>ordained parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments twice in the yeer, or oftner; and</hi> William <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror did the like.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Here learned Mr. <hi>Bencher</hi> ſhews his Reading. So the <hi>old Britains</hi> went <hi>naked</hi> before <hi>Christ's</hi> time, and many <hi>odd faſhions</hi> came up in the times of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the <hi>Danes,</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> both in Cloaths and Government. Doth this oblige us to the like now? To what end then is this old <hi>thred-bare ſtuff</hi> brought hither to ſtuff his Pamphlet? I have granted over and over, that Parliaments of old were ſo frequent as he ſaith: but I ſuppoſe it would do the people of <hi>England</hi> little ſervice to tell them what a ſort of Parliaments they were, and how compoſed of Lords Spiritual and Temporal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſuppoſe we ſhould be loth to have ſuch Parliaments now. And yet according to Mr. <hi>Bencher's</hi> learned way of Arguing, if we be obliged to one Circumſtance of Example, we are alſo as much bound to obſerve the other. If to the timing of Parliaments as of old, then alſo to the form and manner of them. But Time and Law having provided better things for the people, his Worſhip's way of arguing Us into old Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons again is as pertinent, as if he would prove <hi>John a Nokes</hi> ſhould be bound to make all good that was deviſed by his <hi>ſixteen hundred and tenth great-great-great-Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>John-a-Stiles,</hi> if the Writings of the Deviſe were to be found in <hi>Dunwallo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>BENCHER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I must tell you, there are thoſe that affirm the Laws for</hi> Annual Parliaments <hi>to be</hi> Muſty obſolete Statutes whoſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42173:25"/>
ſtrength and life are devoured by Time. <hi>But it is enough to ſtop their mouthes, that they have been Declared by two Parliaments, within forty yeers last past, to be the Laws of our Realm.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Who are they that are ſo weak-headed as to ſay they are <hi>Muſty</hi> and <hi>Obſolete?</hi> Neither his Majeſtie nor his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will give 'em thanks for ſaying ſo: nor doth the Prorogation need ſuch an Allegation to maintain it good. I have ſufficiently ſhewn, that the ſence of the two Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, if entirely taken, makes fully for the Right of the King to judge whether Parliaments Annually be needful or not: and that within Forty yeers time two Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have confirm'd their Frequencie, and ſo frequent as every yeer, or oftner, if his Majeſtie ſee Occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their Aſſembling ſo often. Therefore he hath much more reaſon to defend them, than the <hi>Faction</hi> hath to make ſuch ado about them, unleſs they could get more Credit to their <hi>own Cauſe</hi> by a Rational Conſtruction of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>BENCHER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord</hi> Coke <hi>ſaith,</hi> Inſtit. part 1. page 81. <hi>That no Act of Parliament can loſe its force, or be antiquated by</hi> Non-uſer, <hi>unleſs the Reaſon of it fail, and by change of time it become a publike Miſchief,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>It ſeems the <hi>Reaſon</hi> for having <hi>conſtant yeerly Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> did fail in <hi>Edward</hi> the Third's time, or elſe his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42173:26"/>
had never deviſed thoſe two Statutes, and put in the words IF NEED BE, ſo far to change the <hi>ancient Cuſtom</hi> of their frequencie, as not to hold them ſo often, unleſs Need require; and of that Neceſſity who can be a Judge but the King, whom our Laws have Hereditarily inveſted with all the Rights of Government, of which this ſort of Judicatory power is a principal? Wherefore, the Reaſon of the <hi>ancient frequencie</hi> being out of date long ſince, it was well done by this Parliament, upon new Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon more ſuitable to the Condition and Temper of this Age, to aſcertain us of holding Parliaments in the future with <hi>frequencie</hi> more convenient for us.</p>
               <p>However, 'tis worth the obſervation what his Maſter-ſhip doth grant, that <hi>Non-uſer</hi> may antiquate Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and make them loſe their Force, <hi>if the Reaſon of them fail,</hi> or <hi>if by change of time they become a Publike Miſchief.</hi> As for the Reaſon of King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Act, I have ſhewn already that his Parliament had nothing in their Reaſon of making them, that ſavours of the Old Cuſtom of <hi>yeerly frequencie,</hi> otherwiſe than with Condition there <hi>ſhall be need:</hi> nor do they contain any ſence that gives us cauſe to plead that they are <hi>antiquated,</hi> or to deſire an antiquation of them; becauſe to Repeal them would be an Injury to the King. But next let me adde this, that in the two late <hi>Triennial Acts</hi> it is implied, that in theſe days things are alter'd to ſuch a paſs, that there was high Reaſon to be no longer bound to the ancient Cuſtom of that <hi>Annual frequencie</hi> which his Maſterſhip pleads for; and thereby you have the Determination of two whole Parliaments, the FORTY ONE Parliament and this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that the Reaſon of the ſaid <hi>Cuſtom at Common law</hi> fails, and that publike Inconveniences, if not publike Miſchief, would follow, if it were practiſed in our time, or elſe 'tis in reaſon to be ſuppoſed they never would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42173:26"/>
have alter'd it. Therefore, ſeeing his <hi>Maſterſhip</hi> doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit what I have made evident in the foregoing part of this Diſcourſe, that there hath been a <hi>Non-uſer</hi> of King <hi>Edward</hi>'s two Statutes, in any ſuch ſence as he and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows do impoſe, they having never been ſo put in practice by <hi>Edward</hi> himſelf, or by any ſucceeding King to this day, we with all aſſurance conclude, that a pleading of <hi>Non-uſer</hi> is a good Plea againſt the two Statute's being in force for ſuch an <hi>abſolute yeerly frequencie,</hi> as the Faction doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate into the mindes of the people: Eſpecially when two Parliaments before-nam'd have judged, that <hi>Reaſon</hi> of publike Good and Convenience now lies againſt having them ſo frequent as within a yeer, and that the time of <hi>Three yeers</hi> is ſoon enough, <hi>unleſs there be need.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing then but a ſpirit of <hi>Sedition</hi> or <hi>Treaſon</hi> would have fixed <hi>ſuch a Conſtruction</hi> as theſe men have lately made upon the ſaid Statutes, with a mighty Clamour, as if <hi>Noiſe</hi> would carry it among reaſonable men. But their <hi>Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> being every way proved naught, all the Arguments founded upon that Bottom do neceſſarily fall; and Maſter <hi>Bencher</hi> and the reſt of the Diſputants ought to be tried before a <hi>Bench</hi> of <hi>Academian Sophiſters,</hi> that they may be brought under Correction for that wretched Beggery, <hi>A Begging of the Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A way then with the <hi>Queſtions</hi> with which he ſtuffs up all the reſt of his Book, becauſe they are grounded upon the ſame ſad account of <hi>Petitio Principii,</hi> and ſo are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether impertinent to the Point in hand, till they can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prove their <hi>own Conſtruction</hi> of the <hi>two Statutes</hi> to be a right one, or that thoſe Statutes were at any time ſince their making put in uſe and practice, upon ſuppoſal of any ſuch abſolute Meaning as he and his <hi>Fellow-writers</hi> would faſten upon them. His <hi>Questions</hi> follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:42173:27"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>BENCHER.</head>
                  <p>1. <hi>Whether the Statutes for yeerly Parliaments may be diſpenſed with by the King's Soveraign Power and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, being (as ſome ſay) onely Counſels and Advices to the King, not obligatory.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Who are thoſe <hi>ſome</hi> that ſay ſo? If any did, they talkt as idly as Maſter <hi>Bencher</hi> writes, and as little to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: for his <hi>Maſterſhip</hi> hereupon ſtarts up an invidious Queſtion, <hi>Whether the King may diſpence with Laws and Statutes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I rather ſuppoſe the SOME <hi>that ſay ſo</hi> never were men of God's making, but mere <hi>men of ſtraw</hi> ſet up by Maſter <hi>Bencher,</hi> for a Tryal of his own Skill in Confutation and Conqueſt, and to entertain his Majeſties ſubjects with Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals that there is ſtrange Doctrine at Court in matter of Law; that ſo himſelf may take occaſion to lug in a long diſcourſe to prove the Negative, that his Majeſtie cannot diſpence. But know once for all, that there is none under heaven who can be more tender of the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie of Law and Legal Conſtitutions than the King Himſelf is, eſpecially ſuch as are <hi>Parliamentary:</hi> and it would be the joy of the <hi>Faction</hi> if they could really finde Him otherwiſe; or if they could by any <hi>Tricks of State,</hi> (ſuch as were ſhewn in <hi>ſeveral Seſſions</hi> of Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore laſt <hi>February-Seſſion)</hi> play in upon Him the neceſſity of having recourſe to that <hi>Supreme Law,</hi> the Idol of the FORTY ONE Parliament <hi>(Salus Populi ſuprema lex)</hi> to ſave Himſelf and his People from ſuch Confuſions and Deſtructions as the Counſels of the <hi>Faction,</hi> if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42173:27"/>
will bring upon us. I may well call it the <hi>Idol</hi> of that Parliament, conſidering how they abuſed that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime</hi> in a cauſleſs uſing it againſt his Majeſties Father, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſly pleading the <hi>Safety of the People</hi> to juſtifie what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they did, as confidently as if the People could have been ſaved no other way, if they had kept within the Bounds of <hi>Ordinary law.</hi> But the <hi>ordinary path</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> is that which his Majeſtie deſires to walk in; and to prove the Truth of this, we need onely to recollect the paſt Provocations given Him by the late extravagances of ſome men, which would have provoked any Prince leſs patient, to other Courſes than he hath taken, to ſecure Himſelf, his Affairs, his Friends, and the Intereſt of his Crown. And as to that point of the <hi>Prorogation,</hi> he did not thereby aſſume to Himſelf any power to <hi>diſpence</hi> with the Laws relating to the Courſe of Parliament, but kept within the Bound of Law, as is abundantly proved: Therefore the dragging in this <hi>Queſtion</hi> of yours muſt needs be very impertinent, as well as maliciouſly meant, good Maſter <hi>Bencher;</hi> and ſo are all the vile Inferences that you have made thereupon to catch the People.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>BENCHER.</head>
                  <p>2. His Second Point under queſtion is, <hi>Whether the Kings diſmiſſion of the Parliament without any day ſet for their return, and their continuing ſo beyond a yeer, be a</hi> Diſſolution? <hi>or whether ſuch a</hi> failer <hi>in Time onely may by Act of Law diſſolve a Parliament, even against the Will of the King?</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>So, ſo; All is out now. The main Point they drive at
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42173:28"/>
is, to Diſſolve the Parliament againſt the Will of the King: but what pretence hath the <hi>Bencher</hi> for declaring it Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved? Not a tittle more than what was alledged by the DISSOLVER. He ſaid, Diſmiſſion of a Parliament <hi>ſine Die</hi> amounts to a Diſſolution. But how comes it, that the Fifteenth of <hi>February,</hi> the day to which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was prorogued or diſmiſſed, is reckoned to be <hi>No day?</hi> They prove this <hi>as faſt as Hops,</hi> becauſe it is to be reckoned <hi>No day in conſtruction of Law,</hi> in regard it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded three months beyond the term of <hi>Twelve,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Twelve no Parliament can by Law live; and dying at the yeers end, it cannot be made alive again by <hi>Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</hi> This is a very fine and quick diſpatch: but 'tis to be anſwer'd too <hi>as faſt as Hops</hi> now, that King <hi>Edward</hi> and his Statutes meant no ſuch quick Births and ſudden Deaths of <hi>Parliaments</hi> as theſe men would perſwade us: ſo that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Clouds that ſome perſons raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, the 15th of <hi>February</hi> appear'd a <hi>fair day in Law,</hi> and to all other intents and purpoſes; and it gave us day-light enough to diſcern the vanity and folly of the <hi>Faction,</hi> and its chiefeſt Advocates, with their matchleſs Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, grounded upon the Conſtruction of no better Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers than Maſter <hi>Bencher</hi> himſelf and his <hi>fellows</hi> appear to be, <hi>viz. pitiful Logicians, Lack-learning Lawyers:</hi> for, they are his own words, which in pag. 22. he frankly beſtows upon all <hi>Gentlemen of the long Robe,</hi> that are of leſs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and more underſtanding. Therefore his Friend the new-elected <hi>Member</hi> may come up to Town if he pleaſe; for the <hi>Body</hi> to which he belongs is yet alive, and like to continue in good Health, notwithſtanding all the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours that have been uſed to put it out of temper.</p>
               <p>Thus far I have been giving you the utmoſt that hath been argued by all the <hi>Three books</hi> which the <hi>Projecting Faction</hi> have hitherto proclaimed to be <hi>unanſwerable:</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:42173:28"/>
But now you ſee, a very little Learning in Law, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Law on their ſide, goes a great way with them: They are better at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p-cry,</hi> and <hi>Out-cry,</hi> and <hi>Down-cry,</hi> and juſt ſo much Conſtruction of Law and Goſpel as will ſerve to beat up Drums in the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> for, that is the way of doing their work, without Wit or Reaſon. And therefore I was willing to ſpend the more time about thoſe Books, that I might not omit any one thing in them that is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable; that ſo the World may ſee how ſmall cauſe they have for all their Clamour; and that the Parliament did Juſtice, when they condemned ſo many of theſe <hi>Prints</hi> as came to their hands, to be fired by the hand of the Hang-man.</p>
               <p>The next Pamphlet that comes to hand is a Thing that pretends to little of Argument, but takes occaſion from the Impriſonment of the Four Lords to rail at and revile and ſcandalize the whole Government moſt ſufficiently, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the <hi>Parliament</hi> in the moſt odious terms that could be invented.</p>
               <p>It is Intituled, <hi>A Narrative of the cauſe and manner of the Impriſonment of the Lords, now cloſe Priſoners in the Tower of</hi> London. And it is intended to walk abroad among the People, to perſwade them that their Lordſhips ſuffer Martyrdom for maintaining the Nation's Rights and Liberties: whereas the very Truth is, they are but <hi>one mans Martyrs,</hi> being miſled by him. 'Tis <hi>a little leven that leveneth the whole lump. Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindles! Can a man take fire into his boſome and not be burnt?</hi> Nay, though it be but a <hi>ſmall Squib,</hi> it will do the Feat if it be not well put out, eſpecially on the return of <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon-days.</hi> Therefore I will be ſo charitable, as not to think that all the <hi>Four Lords</hi> had a hand in this malicious work. My reaſon is, It can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42173:29"/>
conſiſt with a <hi>Man of Honour,</hi> unleſs he be one that hath often forfeited it, to be petitioning his Prince, and at the ſame time to be plotting a Libel againſt Him. It was about the time that the <hi>Petition</hi> was deliver'd to the King at <hi>Newmarket</hi> in <hi>April</hi> laſt, that this <hi>Printed Narrative</hi> came to my hand; and after peruſal, finding it was full fraught with <hi>Revenges</hi> and <hi>Falſities,</hi> it proved the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my now taking Pen in hand, to cure all the <hi>Tetters of State</hi> that are to be cured with <hi>Ink;</hi> of which none is ſo virulent and <hi>Corroſive</hi> as this. We expect to ſee it more openly publiſhed, as ſoon as the <hi>Faction</hi> ſhall finde the lucky day they hope for: but in the mean while the Books are kept in and <hi>ready dormant</hi> all, except thoſe which they craftily convey in private, to inflame their <hi>Party</hi> in City and Country againſt <hi>this Parliament.</hi> It begins thus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>On Thurſday the 15th of</hi> February, <hi>the</hi> Parliament <hi>(as they call themſelves) or the</hi> Convention <hi>(as I hear others generally call them) met. And at the ſame time, a vast number of people filled</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall, <hi>the</hi> Court of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, <hi>the</hi> Painted Chamber, <hi>the</hi> Lobbies, <hi>and all places neer the</hi> Parliament-houſe; <hi>that the like was never ſeen upon the Meeting of this, or of any other Parliament in our memory. They did earnestly deſire and expect they would declare themſelves to be No Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>There was little difference betwixt the number of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at the opening of that <hi>February-Seſſion,</hi> and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that went to be at the Opening of other Seſſions of Parliament. But how weak ſoever this <hi>Narrator</hi>'s Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42173:29"/>
be, I and Thouſands more can remember, and the Citie of <hi>London</hi> can, and will remember, what they got by it, when it began to be <hi>Flowing water</hi> of Rebellion with the <hi>ſame Faction</hi> in 1641, what a mighty Inundation of the Multitude they ſent down to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to fill that <hi>Hall,</hi> and beſides the <hi>Lobbies, Court of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>queſts, Court of Wards,</hi> and <hi>Painted Chamber,</hi> that whole Citie, <hi>White-hall,</hi> the <hi>Strand</hi> and All, was filled with <hi>a Mad Crew,</hi> crying out upon <hi>King, Evil Counſellors, Biſhops, French</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Popery, Fears, Jealouſies,</hi> and <hi>Grievances.</hi> And as Cats are let blood in the Ear many times by old women to cure the <hi>Shingles,</hi> ſo the whole <hi>Poſſe</hi> of <hi>Sermoning Matrons</hi> (the chief Gariſon of the <hi>Presbyterian Clergie)</hi> made a Sally out o'th' Citie, and went down alſo to bleed <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as the onely means to cure all our Evils.</p>
               <p>I ſhould not mention theſe things, but that I am forced with grief of heart to it, now that I ſee the ſame Humours would be preached about anew by the ſame impenitent <hi>reſtleſs Faction,</hi> if they could but cheat the <hi>Old men</hi> again, who ſaw and cannot forget theſe things ſo eaſily; but the <hi>Faction</hi> now delude the <hi>Younger men,</hi> who never ſaw yet a Bleeding, nor the ſport of Bear-baiting the King's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Privie Counſellers, in whom lies all His Safety at ſuch a ſeaſon. I remember what ſome of the <hi>Leaders</hi> then ſaid, <hi>Have we got him to part with</hi> Strafford? <hi>Then he muſt deny us nothing; the reſt at Court, being frighted, will fall in with us to ſave themſelves:</hi> and ſo it proved too true of too many of them, that for their childrens ſakes I forbear the naming. But by this means thoſe <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> got the <hi>Foot-ball before 'em,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> was fain to run for it, but could never recover it.</p>
               <p>And then what got the Nation by it? I think we all know: but that the <hi>young men</hi> of the Citie may have
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42173:30"/>
an Account of the Gains of their <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> take it as follows, it having been drawn up by one that was in thoſe days a Member of Parliament. Some concern the Citie alone, and ſome were charged upon both Citie and Country.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>A Tax called the</hi> Royal Subſidie <hi>of Three hundred thouſand pounds.</hi> (I think it was the Tax they got the King to paſs, to pay the <hi>Scotch Presbyterian</hi> Army, which themſelves had brought a little before into this Kingdom to compaſs their Ends.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. Poll-money.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Free Loans and Contributions upon the</hi> Publike Faith, of <hi>Money, Plate, Thimbles, Bodkins, Horſe, Arms,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>amounting to a vaſt incredible ſum.</hi> (I remember, and mine eyes ſaw at <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> Plate brought in out of the Citizens houſes, and heaped up like huge Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piles.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Iriſh Adventure money</hi> (moſt out of this Citie) <hi>for purchaſe of lands in</hi> Ireland (which the King's Father called <hi>a dividing of the Bears skin before they had conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The Weekly Meal-money;</hi> (that is to ſay, the Citizens ſpared a Meal out of their own bellies, converting the value of it into Caſh, to be preſented after their Plate.)</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>Citie loan, after the rate of fifty Subſidies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>The Aſſeſment of Money to bring on a Presbyterian Army of Scots a ſecond time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>The Fifth and Twentieth part of men's eſtates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>The Weekly Aſſeſment for the Lord General</hi> Eſſex <hi>his Army.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>The Weekly (or Monthly) Aſſeſment for Sir</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Fairfax<hi>'s</hi> Army.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>The Weekly Aſſeſment for the ſecond</hi> Scotch Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian <hi>Army after it had entered</hi> England.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:42173:30"/>
12. <hi>The Weekly Aſſeſment for the</hi> Britiſh <hi>Army in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>The Weekly Aſſeſment for my Lord of</hi> Mancheſter<hi>'s Army.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Free Quarter connived at by the Rulers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Sequeſtrations of the King's, Queen's, and Prince's Revenue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Sequeſtrations and Plunders by Committees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Exciſe upon all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon the Gentleman who drew up this <hi>Account</hi> wrote thus: <hi>[By theſe ſeveral Ways and Taxes, about</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Millions <hi>in Money and Money's worth were milked out of the Nation, the moſt part out of this Citie; and that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (as the</hi> Pope <hi>did once) might well have called England</hi> Puteum inexhauſtum. <hi>A vaſt Treaſure it was! ſuch a one as nothing but a long Peace could have impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and nothing but</hi> pious Frauds, <hi>many Follies, and a Mad War could diſſipate.</hi> And yet all this prodigious Sum was drained away and ſpent before the yeer 1647. in but ſix years; ſo that we do not reckon the vaſt Sums fetcht out of the Citie and Kingdom, to carry on the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Wars which ſprang out of this, in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> betwixt 1647 and 1654. amounting to another vaſt Sum of Moneys, of which I am not able to give any Account.</p>
               <p>I might reckon alſo the many Tuns of Tears and Blood that were drawn out of the eyes and ſides of theſe three Nations, which the <hi>Presbyterian Faction</hi> can never waſh off without Tears of Repentance. But let it not be the Repentance of <hi>Judas;</hi> ſuch a one as they made in 1648. when they ſaw the <hi>Ball of Empire</hi> caught out of their hands into the hands of <hi>Cromwel;</hi> and mourned for that, not for the completed Ruine of the King and his Family; which themſelves firſt began, and carried on as far as they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42173:31"/>
could. And they muſt look to have it mention'd, till they leave off reviving their <hi>old Tricks</hi> of undermining the Government, and embroiling the Nation. But this may ſerve at preſent, to let the <hi>Young men</hi> as well as the <hi>old</hi> ſee what the Citie and Kingdom got by being led by the Noſe to <hi>Westminſter</hi> for a Crying down and ſhifting of Governours and State-Miniſters under the King; of whoſe Faults they knew nothing but what they took up upon the Credit of <hi>pretended Patriots,</hi> but really crafty <hi>deſigning publike Enemies,</hi> as they afterwards appeared to be.</p>
               <p>And you perceive alſo how falſe this <hi>Narrator</hi> is, when he tells you, that in the memory of man there never was before <hi>February</hi> laſt, ſuch a flocking of people to <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> at the opening of a Seſſion of Parliament.</p>
               <p>But what went the people out to ſee? <hi>They went to ſee a Reed ſhaken with the wind.</hi> But the Wind brought on a Storm upon thoſe that would have ſhaken the Foundation of both Houſes; which ſeeing they could not do, a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution is reſolved on in mere ſpight, that 'tis now no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, but a <hi>Convention;</hi> which certainly deſerves a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere <hi>Animadverſion</hi> of State upon ſuch as would turn up the Foundation upon which we ſtand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When the King was come, the Commons were ſent for up to the Lords Houſe, where I made a ſhift to croud in and hear. The King and Lord Chancellor each of them made a Speech worthy your conſideration, Copies whereof I have here ſent you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:42173:31"/>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>But he is as falſe here alſo, as he was before in the other: for I finde neither of thoſe <hi>Speeches</hi> incloſed in this <hi>Print.</hi> He will be wary enough of printing them, becauſe they are worthy to be often read and conſider'd by all the people, in order to their ſatisfaction touching the juſtice, prudence and candour of his Majeſtie's Government: therefore I muſt needs give you ſhort Heads of the Kings Speech, that the ſiniſter intents and boiſterous invective diſcourſes of <hi>ſome men</hi> may be the better underſtood.</p>
               <p>The King in his Speech of the 15 of <hi>February</hi> told his Lords, and the Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons: <hi>That he had called them together again after a long Proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they might have an opportunity to repair the Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of the foregoing Seſſion, and to recover and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the right uſe and end of Parliaments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he was reſolved to let the World ſee, that it ſhould not be his fault if they be not made happie by their Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he plainly declared he came prepared to give them all ſatisfaction and ſecurity in the great concerns of the Proteſtant Religion, as it is eſtabliſhed in the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>that can conſiſt with reaſon and Chriſtian prudence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that he declared as freely, that he is ready to grant a further ſecuring of our Liberties and Properties, by as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Laws as they ſhall propoſe, and can conſiſt with the Government; without which there will be neither Liberty nor Property left to any man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he would have all men judge, who is moſt for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government, they that foment ſuch differences as tend to diſſolve all Parliaments, or He, that would preſerve this and all Parliaments from being made uſeleſs by ſuch Diſſentions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:42173:32"/>
                  <hi>That if theſe good Ends ſhould happen to be diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, He calls God and men to witneſs, that the misfortune of that diſappointment ſhall not lie at his dore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What can be more deſired from a gracious King? But 'tis not the mode, nor agreeable to the temper and buſineſs of ſome men in the world, to reſt as men ſatisfied with Reaſon, though perhaps they be. Theſe are they at whoſe dore the guilt of <hi>Parliamentary Conſtitutions</hi> muſt lie, if ever God for our ſins ſhould permit them to proceed. For, <hi>they of the Faction</hi> cannot fiſh in the waters of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; they would have a Senate with <hi>Oligarchs</hi> over it, in ſtead of a <hi>Monarch.</hi> For the <hi>Narrator</hi> ſaith we ought not to uſe the word <hi>Parliament</hi> now; but the word <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> is better.</p>
               <p>Nor is it any part of the <hi>Faction</hi>'s buſineſs to be content with the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Religion,</hi> or <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property;</hi> theſe are words which they know how to make uſe of, by ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling them as flowers of Rhetorick in all their Writings and Diſcourſes: they work upon the People with them, as <hi>Witches</hi> do with <hi>Charms, Characters,</hi> and <hi>Spells,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch the Multitude with an opinion againſt the Court, and that all is in danger that way, and that themſelves are the onely Patrons and Patriots, when in the mean time they onely tickle them like <hi>Trouts</hi> with theſe things, to catch them, and enſlave them to their own deſignes and humours, for pulling the Government in pieces; which is the only Bulwark of <hi>Religion, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property:</hi> For, as the King well ſaith before, without this there will be neither Religion, Liberty, Property nor Safety left to any man. The Truth whereof we found by woful experience, which enſued after the very ſame Witchcrafts had bereaved the people of their Senſes in FORTY ONE to run headlong into Civil Wars, which laſted ſo long, till Twenty yeers Suffering under loſs of Religion, Liberty, Property, Safety,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42173:32"/>
Government, and all, made them long and ſigh after their Soveraign Lord again as the onely Reſtorer.</p>
               <p>Look back then once again upon thoſe ſhort Heads of <hi>His Majesties Speech</hi> with an impartial eye, and you have in view ſo many demonſtrations of Wiſdom, Moderation, Tenderneſs for <hi>this Parliament,</hi> and the future being of Parliaments in their ancient Legal ſtate; as alſo of Love and Kindneſs towards his People, that more cannot be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd by Man to caſt out the devil of Jealouſie, and keep it from haunting the Houſes of this people any more.</p>
               <p>His Majeſtie in one of the Heads ſaith to this effect; That without keeping within the compaſs of the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as the Laws have ſtated every part of it, <hi>viz.</hi> in a <hi>delicate Medium</hi> betwixt the <hi>Regal Prerogative</hi> and the <hi>Parliamentary Right and Liberty of the people,</hi> ſo as both may be preſerved entire, unto Kings and unto Parliaments, in their ſeveral Stations, neither <hi>Religion, Liberty, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty,</hi> nor <hi>Safety,</hi> nor <hi>Parliaments,</hi> can be maintain'd. The Reaſon is plain, becauſe the <hi>Law of the land,</hi> which is the Band that ties all together, being once broken by any one of the Parties, they immediately fall aſunder, and will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be cleft into a thouſand pieces, and the <hi>Parliamentary Conſtitution</hi> not eaſily be reſtored, as it appeared upon the FORTY ONE Diviſions, for Twenty yeers together. <hi>Experience</hi> (ſaith the Proverb) <hi>is the Miſtreſs of Fools.</hi> Muſt we always then be Fooling for new Experiments of our <hi>old Foolery?</hi> One would think we ſhould have been wiſer by this time, than to ſuffer the <hi>ſame Faction</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant us any more.</p>
               <p>But becauſe a better Deſcription of <hi>Kingly</hi> and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Interest</hi> of Government cannot be had than what was deſcribed by the Pen of His Majeſties Royal Father, in His Anſwer to the <hi>Nineteen Propoſitions,</hi> preſented to him by that Parliament of the <hi>Faction, anno</hi> 1642. <hi>June</hi> 2.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42173:33"/>
let me here ſet it down, in regard it will be the beſt Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of poſterity what to do in like Caſes, to prevent fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Troubles that may ariſe again, through mens acting <hi>old Cheats</hi> over and over. His words are theſe: <hi>[There being Three kindes of Government among men;</hi> Abſolute Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, <hi>and</hi> Democracy, <hi>and all theſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving particular inconveniences, the experience and wiſdom of our Ancestors hath ſo moulded our Government in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>out of a</hi> Mixture of all Three, <hi>as to give this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (ſo far as Humane wiſdom can provide) the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies of the Three, without the Inconveniencies of any One, as long as the</hi> Balance <hi>hangs even between the</hi> Three Eſtates, <hi>and while they run joyntly on in their proper Chanels, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting verdure and fertility in the Meadows on both ſides) and while there is no overflowing of either on either ſide, to raiſe a Deluge or Inundation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this Kingdom the Laws are joyntly made by a</hi> King, <hi>by</hi> a Houſe of Peers, <hi>and by</hi> a Houſe of Commons <hi>choſen by the People, all having free Votes and particular Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The Government according to our Laws, is truſted to the</hi> King, <hi>with power of Treaties of War and Peace, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> Peers, <hi>of chuſing Officers and Counſellers</hi> for State, Judges <hi>for Law,</hi> Commanders <hi>for Forts and Castles,</hi> giving Commiſſions <hi>for raiſing men to make War abroad, or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt Invaſions or Inſurrections at home, Benefit of Confiſcations, power of Pardoning, and ſome more of the like kinde, are placed in the King. And this</hi> Monarchy <hi>thus regulated, having this power to preſerve that Authority without which it would be diſabled to preſerve the Laws in their force, and the Subjects in their Liberties and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, is intended to draw to him ſuch a Reſpect and Relation from the Great Ones, as may hinder the Ills of Diviſion and Faction, and procure ſuch a Fear and Reverence from the</hi> People, <hi>as may hinder Tumults, Violence, and Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:42173:33"/>
                  <hi>Again, that the</hi> Prince <hi>may not make uſe of this high and perpetual Power to the hurt of thoſe for whoſe good he hath it, and make uſe of the name of Publike Neceſſity for the gain of his private Favourites and Followers, to the detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his People, the Houſe of Commons (an excellent Conſerver of Liberty, but never intended for any</hi> Share <hi>in the Government, or for the chuſing of them that ſhould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern) is ſoly intruſted with the firſt Propoſition concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing levies of Moneys, which are the ſinews of Peace as well as War, and with the Impeaching of thoſe, who for their own ends, though countenanced by any ſurreptitiouſly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Command of the King, have violated that Law, which he is bound (when he knoweth it) to protect, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of which they were bound to Adviſe him, at least not to ſerve him in the contrary. And the Lords being truſted with a</hi> Judiciary power, <hi>are an excellent Skreen and Bank between the Prince and the People, to aſſist each againſt any Incroachments of the other, and by just Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to preſerve that law, which ought to be the Rule of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of the Three.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not have tranſcribed this, but that I conceive it impoſſible to make a more excellent Delineation of the ſeveral Concerns of the King and his Subjects in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our Engliſh Government, that every one may underſtand what is their due by Law, and how Monſtrous the <hi>Demands</hi> were in thoſe <hi>Nineteen Propoſitions,</hi> the firſt of which was: <hi>[That thoſe Lords and others of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Privie Council, and ſuch</hi> great Officers and Miniſters of State, <hi>either at home or beyond the Seas, may be put from your Privie Council, and from thoſe Offices and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, excepting ſuch as ſhall be approved of by both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> &amp;c.] The reſt of the Demands were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to this. But what anſwer'd the King to theſe things? <hi>[Theſe</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>being paſſed, We may be waited</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:42173:34"/>
                  <hi>on bare-headed, We may have Our hand kiſs'd; the Stile of Majestie continued to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; and the King's Authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by both Houſes of Parliament may be ſtill the Stile of your Commands: We may have Swords and Maces car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried before <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, and pleaſe our Self with the ſight of a Sword and Scepter, (and yet even theſe Twigs would not long flouriſh, after the Stock upon which they grew becomes dead) but as to true and real Power We ſhould remain but</hi> the out-ſide, <hi>but the</hi> Picture, <hi>but the</hi> Signe <hi>of a King. We were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver willing that Our Parliament ſhould debate, reſolve and tranſact ſuch matters as are proper for them, as far as they are proper for them, and We heartily wiſh that they would be careful, not to extend their Debates and Reſolutions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what is proper to them,</hi> &amp;c.] But alas, inſtead of hearkening to this, they without reaſon carried all before them like a mighty Stream, and ſo the fatal Wars came on, becauſe the King would not be unking'd, by giving away the Flowers of his Crown: If he would not part with 'em by ſuch fair means, they reſolved to have 'em by foul. But remember this, that God ſuffer'd not any of the <hi>firſt Hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurs</hi> and Beginners, to reap any Comfort by the Buſineſs: which (as all Hiſtories will ſhew us) is the common Fate of ſuch Undertakers. And it were well, if I had room here to make a Stand, to give you a Relation of ours here in <hi>England.</hi> But 'tis time now to return to the <hi>Narrator,</hi> and tell him, all this kinde of doings was at <hi>Westminſter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the memory of man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As ſoon as the Speeches were made, and the Commons were withdrawn, a Bill was offered to be read. But the Duke of</hi> Buckingham <hi>deſired to be heard first.</hi> Well then, what ſaid the Duke? <hi>It was clear to him the Parliament was Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved:</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:42173:34"/>
                     <hi>for which opinion he gave his Reaſons; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the ſum of all that was ſaid to prove tho diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, I ſhall give you as good and as brief an account of them as I can.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>The ſum of that Speech (as the <hi>Narrator</hi> hath printed it) amounts but to two pages: I have a written Copie of it by me, and could Animadvert upon it; but I would not ſtrip one of the fineſt Courtiers of the world for leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide out of his proper Element. I am tender of him in many Reſpects; but 'tis both my trouble and my won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the <hi>Narrator</hi> prints him among the <hi>Martyrs</hi> that ſuffer for the ſake of a <hi>FACTION;</hi> who perſecuted the Illuſtrious Duke his Lordſhips father, both in and out of Parliament, till he fell their Sacrifice by the hand of <hi>Felton,</hi> and left him the Inheriter of all thoſe Honours and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, which flow'd from the Bounty of our Kings. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, return, Noble Lord, (if it may be) by the way of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence, and take Noble <hi>Salisbury</hi> along with you well prepared, whoſe wiſe Grandfather was the great Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in making way for that happie Succeſſion, which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited both theſe Kingdoms under the old name of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> I have here (my Lord Duke) taken ſome pains to convince you and all the World; and I hope I have done it. If any thing more could be done for you, I would do it, in hope of your Penitence: and I hope I do not in vain perſwade you, becauſe I think your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not made of the ſame metal with a man's, that (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>hath been ſeared with a red-hot Iron.</hi> Think not that I court you; or that I think your fault (as Circumſtances were when you committed it) hath left you capable of pardon from any but the moſt merciful of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42173:35"/>
Kings, and the extreme commiſeration of your Peers, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I could think the Deſtruction of ſuch a Parliament as this a ſmall matter, (for, this a quick Diſſolution would in probability amount to). I would not have a tittle to ſay for you, if I did not believe who it was that drew you in to the Buſineſs: which whether REASON of STATE can excuſe, is a weighty Queſtion. If there were any thing in the Arguments of your Speech, more than what was ſaid in other words by the <hi>Conſiderator,</hi> and the <hi>Diſſolver,</hi> I would give you the ſatisfaction of handling it; but it ſeems to me to be but a mere REHEARSAL, which hath in it onely more of Wit, and of a Gentleman, than of the Reaſon of Law and a Lawyer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No ſooner had the Duke</hi> ended his Speech, <hi>but my Lord</hi> Fretchvil <hi>moved to have him called to the Bar,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>This <hi>Narrator</hi> preſumes to name many more Lords that ſpake <hi>pro,</hi> and ſome few <hi>con,</hi> that is, againſt the opinion of the Diſſolution. But he ſaith the Lord Chancellor at length undertook to anſwer <hi>all the Arguments that were or ſhould be for a</hi> Diſſolution. If ſo, then it was no wonder that the Houſe was ſoon ſatisfied, and concluded (as the <hi>Narrator</hi> ſaith) that the Queſtion ſhould be laid aſide.</p>
               <p>But I would have told you before, that he ſaith the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> upon the Motion of calling the Duke to the Bar, ſaid, <hi>that it would be the taking away all freedom of ſpeech in Parliament.</hi> That would be troubleſome indeed to his Lordſhip, who hath been a very free ſpeaker in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if we may believe the printed <hi>Letter to a friend in the Country,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Speeches</hi> that went abroad in print under his name. But no more of that. I would have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in me now of the <hi>Lion,</hi> and do paſs him by. His Lordſhip may ſee by theſe <hi>Animadverſions</hi> how little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42173:35"/>
he had in Law for ſo great Confidence in the Speech which the <hi>Narrator</hi> ſaith he made alſo upon the Statutes of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. about <hi>yeerly Parliaments.</hi> I hope he did not ſit a Dictator in the Council of theſe <hi>Printed Diſſolvers.</hi> If he did, 'tis but reaſon the FACTION, or ſome-body elſe, ſhould pay him his Fees.</p>
               <p>But before I part with his Lordſhip, I muſt needs ſhew him his Errour about the point of <hi>freedom of ſpeech in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> and 'tis abſolutely neceſſary that I do it, becauſe 'tis become a villanous Inſinuation uſed by the <hi>Narrator,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>ſcandalous Faction</hi> round the Town, that the Impriſonment of the <hi>four Lords</hi> is done contrary to the ancient Priviledge of Parliament, which is to have a <hi>liberty of ſpeech in all Debates.</hi> As for this Lord, he need not complain; he had enough given him, or rather he took it, if the Speeches printed, with his name to them, be his. Doth <hi>freedom of ſpeech</hi> extend ſo far as to make odious Inſinuations and Reflections upon the King, upon the Crown and its Rights, upon the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of it, upon the Honour of the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> upon the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> upon the <hi>whole Church,</hi> with the <hi>Canons,</hi> the <hi>Homilies,</hi> the 39 <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> and her <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as it relates either to God, Religion, or the Civil obedience due to the King, and the whole Government of State, and the Security of all theſe by an Oath of Allegeance? If his Lordſhip thought that the Law allowed either Peers or Commons <hi>ſuch a liberty of ſpeech,</hi> why did he buſtle ſo diligently and briſkly (as I have been told) to promote a Bill, not long ſince, againſt the ancient way of <hi>Tryal of Peers?</hi> Every body then <hi>ſmelt a Rat</hi> in the Caſe, and ſmiled at his Lordſhips wiſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and his ſecret intent of ſpeaking and acting <hi>beyond Compaſs</hi> upon the open Stage: and therefore I did not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when I did read afterwards in the Pamphlet intituled, <hi>Debates and Arguments for Diſſolving this Parliament,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42173:36"/>
(which was reported to be his) that his Lordſhip was very <hi>angry at the Houſe of Commons</hi> for throwing out the ſaid <hi>Bill of Trial</hi> when it was ſent down to them; and tells the <hi>Commons,</hi> p. 6. <hi>They certainly were grown very high in their own opinion, and had a very low eſteem for the Lords, when they neglected their best friends in the</hi> Houſe of Peers, <hi>and did almoſt with ſcorn refuſe that Bill, intituled,</hi> For the more fair and equal Tryal of Peers. I never ſaw the Bill yet, therefore can ſay nothing more of it; onely I cannot but take notice, that in <hi>the ſame page,</hi> and in many other parts of that Print, a through-revenge is plentifully beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Honour of the Houſe of Commons. Nothing would then ſerve the Turn but they muſt be turned out of doors, Diſſolved, and <hi>a new one</hi> preſently call'd; an inſtance clear enough for diſcovery out of whoſe Quiver this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of <hi>Diſſolution</hi> was firſt ſhot, and of great probability who ſet on the Writers ſince againſt the <hi>Prorogation,</hi> to break the neck of this Parliament, and in it all the hopes of the <hi>Loyal part</hi> of the Nation. And if that aforenamed were the Print of his Lordſhip, I might reckon up out of it, and another Print ſtitcht to the tail of it, the moſt viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Scandals that could be raked together to prepare that Houſe for the rage of the Rabble. But the <hi>Narrator</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſum'd up in few words the ſence of the Author, I leave him here, becauſe the <hi>Narrative</hi> it ſelf will give the Houſe that ſhort Cut by and by.</p>
               <p>In the mean while, if freedom of ſpeaking in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and after that, of Printing All and more than All; that is, of more perhaps than was ſpoken, be to be conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and extended at this rate, know that the old Cuſtoms and Laws Parliamentary in <hi>England</hi> know no ſuch matter. A <hi>freedom of ſpeech</hi> in <hi>Debate</hi> is that which every <hi>Speaker</hi> by ancient Cuſtom, after the Houſe of Commons hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen him, and preſented him to the King, doth petition for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42173:36"/>
to the King on the behalf of all the Members of that Houſe; and it was never yet denied by any of our Kings. The Lords alſo in their Houſe do claim it by Birthright: for, to what end do they meet, if they may not freely debate mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, without which 'tis impoſſible to come to any Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about them? May his hand rot off then that ſhall write a word againſt it. But withal we are to underſtand, there are Bounds, Rules and Laws of ſpeaking in either Houſe of Parliament: for, the Law of Parliaments ever ſuppoſeth, that the Members ought to keep within the compaſs of thoſe Bounds, and obſerve thoſe Rules, both as to the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſpoken and the <hi>manner</hi> of ſpeaking. Every Member hath a Right to be heard, and heard out what he hath to ſay; but then when he hath done, the Houſe to which he belongs hath power to judge, whether he hath ſpoken ill or not; and if ill, then they are the proper Judges to diſpoſe of him to puniſhment according to his deſert: And this the Law ſuppoſeth they will always do, they being intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and intruſted with ſuch Neceſſary Power and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for the good of the King and Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Now this is the Caſe of the moſt Noble <hi>Houſe of Peers.</hi> They have as to the committing of the <hi>Four Lords</hi> to the Tower, not done it becauſe they ſpake; (for they heard out with great patience what they had to ſay) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they judged what their Lordſhips had ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Being of this Parliament, was of moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſequence, againſt the Safety and Good of the King and Kingdom. And to ſay no more of this, the Houſe was ſo unanimous in concurring to their Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, after a debate and conſideration of the matter (as will appear upon ſearch of the Books of that Houſe) that it was with great odds of number carried by the <hi>Temporal Lords alone,</hi> without reckoning in the Biſhops, or the number of Proxies. And the Narrator himſelf confeſſeth
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42173:37"/>
this was agreed on after a full <hi>Hearing</hi> of all that could be ſaid by the four Lords themſelves, or their few Friends; only he mingles many ill-favour'd Reflections and falſe Inſinuations in his Relation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It had been</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>moved alſo by the Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>that the Opinion of the Judges might be declared in the Point.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>All Reverence be given to the Judges in due time and place. This was an arduous Point of a Superlative Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, touching the very Life and Being of a Parliament, in a <hi>conſpiring Factious Seaſon,</hi> infinitely above thoſe ordinary points of Law, touching which that Houſe is wont ſometimes to conſult my Lords the Judges, when their Lordſhips conceive they have need to conſult them. But this was ſo plain a Caſe to their Lordſhips, that having the Judicatory right and power in their own hands, and in ſo tranſcendent an Occaſion, it had been a ſtrange thing to have yeelded to ſuch a Motion, merely to gratifie thoſe whom they had judged Offenders. Nor was it to be ſuppoſed, that the Judges would have undertaken to opinionate about ſo <hi>Supreme a Question,</hi> wherein the Safety of all the Concerns of <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>State</hi> were involved, fit onely for the <hi>Supreme Judicature</hi> to conſider.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was the next day urged by ſome Lords, in the behalf of the</hi> Four Lords, <hi>that three ſeveral times,</hi> viz. 1 Hen. 7. 1 <hi>Qu.</hi> Mary. 1 <hi>Qu.</hi> Eliz. <hi>the very ſame Debate was in Parliament, yet no man queſtioned for moving it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>Whether thoſe Debates were the ſame or not, let the world judge, when as the <hi>Narrator</hi> himſelf confeſſes, it was only about the Forms of the Writs that ſummoned the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42173:37"/>
Parliament that the Queſtion in thoſe days was: But this Queſtion made now was, about the validity of a <hi>Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> and the very being of a Parliament after it. I do not finde in my Lord <hi>Cook's</hi> Treatiſe about the <hi>High Court of Parliament,</hi> that the length of a Prorogation beyond a Years time can diſſolve it; or that <hi>a ſmall flaw</hi> in the Form of the Writ of Summons can invalidate a Parliament. But if it were ſo that it could, yet that is not within the Caſe of this Parliament, whoſe Writ of Summons was never queſtion'd; nor could the Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation have been at all diſputed, but that the <hi>Faction</hi> would be ſo bold and miſchievous as to do it; and with how ſlight a colour of Reaſon, you have already ſeen in theſe paſt Diſcourſes. And now their laſt Clamour is, that the <hi>Houſe of Peers</hi> hath condemned the four Lords to Priſon, for preſuming to argue a <hi>Nullity</hi> of the Parliament: And what follows? The <hi>Diſſolver</hi> told us in his Pamphlet, that a <hi>New Parliament</hi> is to come that ſhall call this to account, and leave a new precedent to the world; <hi>That one Parliament may hang another.</hi> And who knows, but that this ſort of Pen-men, with their Patrons, are continually of Counſel with the deſperate FACTION?</p>
               <p>The reſt of this Writers Pamphlet contains nothing, but a partial Relation of Circumſtances and Ceremonies, which paſſed in calling the Four Lords to the Bar, and about the manner of their Commitment: and then he cloſeth all with a few odious Reflections upon the Lords both Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, and the Houſe of Commons; which here follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATOR.</head>
                  <p>He next proceeds in a jeering manner, to mention a <hi>new Triple League:</hi> but who are they that are this <hi>Triple League?</hi> He names <hi>Biſhops, Court-Lords, and Popiſh Lords,</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:42173:38"/>
                     <hi>who had already broken through the ancient Rules and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Parliament, and all the Laws of</hi> England, <hi>and now would go (according to the new</hi> Court-word) <hi>thorow-ſtitch.</hi> The reſt of the Lords he calls <hi>Allies of the Triple League,</hi> who joyned in the <hi>Commitment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>What, a <hi>Petition</hi> in one hand, and at the ſame time a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> in the other? Muſt it be ſo carried, a Petition to the <hi>King,</hi> and the ſame time a Stab given to his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> great Officers, Biſhops, and all the reſt of the Nobility of the Houſe of Peers that concurred with them to preſerve the Government? I would be loth to call the <hi>Four Lords,</hi> and thoſe few that concurred with them on the other ſide (the <hi>Allies of the FACTION,) A New Triple League;</hi> nor will I; let other men think what they pleaſe. This Jeer ſounds like the <hi>Witticiſm</hi> of one of them, that uſes to take care to print all his witty Sayings and Jeſts, as faſt as he ſpeaks them; eſpecially thoſe againſt the Court and the Biſhops, and Miniſters of State, whom he always dreſſes with this kinde of Flowers, to be offer'd in Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to his own <hi>New Parliament,</hi> as the old Heathen Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers were wont to dreſs their Beaſts to be offer'd up to their Idols: therefore if the word <hi>Thorow-ſtitch</hi> were the Word at Court, what would become of him and his <hi>Triple League,</hi> if this old Parliament ſhould proceed as round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as his intended <hi>New one</hi> would do, if we believe the DISSOLVER?</p>
               <p>Then for the Biſhops in particular, he proceeds thus:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATOR.</head>
                  <p>He ſaith, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder pretence of ſecuring the</hi> Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>by Act of Parliament, one of the deſignes of the</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple League <hi>is; To declare it lawful for our Kings to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists; As is done in a Bill lately ſent down to the Commons from the Lords; and I do not hear of any one Biſhop but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:42173:38"/>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>This is a <hi>Fire-ball</hi> with a witneſs, made up of the moſt dangerous, but falſeſt Ingredients; why then ſhould I be long in extinguiſhing it? For the Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> and their Doctrine, Diſcipline and Government, will be found the ſureſt Fence againſt the coming in of Popery, as well as againſt the Invaſion of the FACTION, and the Slavery of their Diſcipline. Can a greater Provocation be given to the Houſe of Peers and the Biſhops? The Forming of this Bill was committed to ſuch a Committee of Lords and Biſhops, that all our world knows them to be Noble and true, and as firm as a Rock againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Religion; and they took the greateſt care that men in prudence poſſibly could do, to ſecure us from it at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and in future. And whatſoever <hi>the father of lyes</hi> may invent, and the FACTION ſpread abroad to the contrary, to exaſperate and increaſe their own Party, more could hardly be invented for our Religion's ſecurity. Sure I am, it was thought ſo by the Papiſts themſelves; and to be ſo ſevere, that they dreaded nothing more than the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of its paſſing both Houſes; inſomuch that ſome Lords of that Religion oppoſed it what they could, and ſpared not to ſay, that after this they expected nothing but <hi>Fire and Fagot.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <argument>
                  <head>NARRATOR.</head>
                  <p>And that the Houſe of Commons may have their ſhare too of damnable Scandal, he lets fly at them without mercy, and thus he concludes, that they are (moſt of them) either <hi>French or Court-penſioners, Indigent, or Out-law'd perſons, Children, Fools, or ſuch as are ſuperannua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>ANIMADVERSION.</head>
               <p>But why <hi>French</hi> Penſioners, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> How then came the Major part to be for an Alliance with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42173:39"/>
appeared by the late Votes and the Addreſs thereupon to his Majeſty? May not then the other ſide with as much reaſon from thence make the like ungentile and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Concluſion, that there are <hi>Dutch Penſioners too?</hi> 'Tis a miſerable paſs the world is come to, when men ſhall take up Scandals from Malice, Phant'ſie, or Jealouſie, to dart at one another; and at this rate there can be no end, till we have railed our ſelves round before the eyes of all the Nations of the world, and painted out our ſelves with the vileſt Characters, to become a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for their Scorn and Deriſion.</p>
               <p>It were again to ſcandalize thoſe worthy Members of the Commons that he aims at; for any man to undertake to vindicate them, againſt the foul Imputations of a mad unconſcionable ſort of deſperate <hi>Boutefeus.</hi> 'Tis to be hoped the Lords and Gentlemen of both Houſes will take heed of theſe Spirits, and by the ſevereſt ANIMAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERSIONS of Authority and Juſtice, make their own Vindication.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42173:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
